- 你不能过来!     - 甘道夫!
- You cannot pass!     - Gandalf!
我是秘密之火的仆人  安诺之火的使用者
I am a servant of the Secret Fire, wielder of the flame of Anor.
回到阴影处
Go back to the Shadow.
黑暗之火对你不利 乌顿之火!
The dark fire will not avail you, flame of Udun!
你不能过来!
You shall not pass!
不 不能过去!
No! No!
甘道夫!
Gandalf!
快走啊 你这傻瓜
Fly, you fools.
不要啊!
No!
甘道夫!
Gandalf!
佛罗多先生 怎么了?
What is it, Mr. Frodo?
没什么
Nothing.
只是做了个梦
Just a dream.
你能看到底吗?
Can you see the bottom?
别! 别往下看  山姆! 继续走!
No! Don't look down, Sam! Just keep going!
抓住! 抓住! 佛罗多先生!
Catch it! Grab it, Mr. Frodo!
佛罗多先生!
Mr. Frodo!
我想我们找到底部了
I think I've found the bottom.
沼泽和绳索 天知道
Bogs and rope, and goodness knows what.
这不自然  所有这些!
It's not natural. None of it.
- 这里面有什么?     - 没什么
- What's in this?     - Nothing.
只是一些调味品
Just a bit of seasoning.
我在想如果我们某天晚上有只烤鸡什么的
I thought maybe if we was having a roast chicken one night or something.
烤鸡?!
Roast chicken?!
你永远不知道会发生什么
You never know.
山姆  我亲爱的山姆!
Sam. My dear Sam.
那很特别 这是所有郡里最好的盐
It's very special, that. It's the best salt in all the Shire.
是很特别
It is special.
有些像家乡的盐
It's a little bit of home.
我们不能把这些留下来 否则会有人跟着我们下来的
We can't leave this here for someone to follow us down.
谁会跟我们下来 佛罗多先生?
Who's gonna follow us down here, Mr. Frodo?
真的很令人遗憾  那是凯兰崔尔女王给我的
It's a shame, really. Lady Galadriel gave me that.
真正的精灵绳索
Real Elvish rope.
嗯 反正这个绳索也是白给的 倒的确是我打的结
Well, there's nothing for it. It's one of my knots.
这个可不是轻易能够得到的
Won't come free in a hurry.
不愧是真正的精灵绳索
Real Elvish rope.
魔多--一个我们不愿意靠近看的世界
Mordor. The one place in Middle-earth we don't want to see any closer.
却是我们试图去的地方
And it's the one place we're trying to get to.
只是 我们不可能到那里
It's just where we can't get.
我们面对现实吧  佛罗多先生  我们迷路了
Let's face it, Mr. Frodo, we're lost.
我想甘道夫的意思不是让我们这样做
I don't think Gandalf meant for us to come this way.
他也不想让其他很多事发生  山姆
He didn't mean for a lot of things to happen, Sam...
但是还是发生了
...but they did.
佛罗多先生?
Mr. Frodo?
是因为那魔戒 没错吧?
It's the Ring, isn't it?
它越来越有分量了
It's getting heavier.
- 我们还剩什么吃的?     - 让我看看
- What food have we got left?     - Let me see.
有了 棒呆了
Oh, yes. Lovely.
兰巴斯干粮 你瞧
Lembas bread. And look!
更多的兰巴斯干粮
More lembas bread.
通常我不太爱吃怪东西
I don't usually hold with foreign food...
不过这种精灵干粮吃起来还不错
...but this Elvish stuff, it's not bad.
什么都不能影响你的心情 是不是 山姆?
Nothing ever dampens your spirits, does it, Sam?
那些乌云就能
Those rain clouds might.
这地方好眼熟
This looks strangely familiar.
那是因为我们来过了
It's because we've been here before.
我们在兜圈子
We're going in circles.
什么味道那么臭?
What is that horrid stink?
我打赌附近一定有沼泽
I warrant there's a nasty bog nearby.
- 你闻得到吗?     - 可以
- Can you smell it?     - Yes.
我闻到了
I can smell it.
这儿还有别人
We're not alone.
小偷 那些小偷
The thieves. The thieves.
那些臭小偷
The filthy little thieves.
它在哪里?
Where is it?
在哪里?
他们从我们这里把它偷走
They stole it from us.
我的宝物
My precious.
诅咒他们 我们恨他们!
Curse them, we hates them!
那是我们的 我们要拿回!
It's ours, it is, and we wants it!
这是针刺宝剑
This is Sting.
你以前也看过它...
You've seen it before...
对吧 咕鲁?
...haven't you, Gollum?
放开他 否则我就割断你喉咙
Release him or I'll cut your throat.
像火烧的一样疼!
It burns!
烧死我们了!
It burns us!
好冰哦!
It freezes!
臭精灵打造的绳子
Nasty Elves twisted it.
- 快帮我们解开!     - 给我闭嘴!
- Take it off us!     - Quiet, you!
这样不行 魔多的半兽人会听到他鬼叫
It's hopeless. Every Orc in Mordor's going to hear this racket.
- 把他绑起来 留在这儿     - 别!
- Let's just tie him up and leave him.     - No!
那样我们会死的! 会死的!
That would kill us! Kill us!
你死了是活该!
It's no more than you deserve!
也许他的确该死
Maybe he does deserve to die.
不过当我看到他 倒是觉得他很可怜
But now that I see him, I do pity him.
我们对他们好 他们一定会报答
We be nice to them if they be nice to us.
快帮我们解开
Take it off us.
我们发誓会按你的吩咐去办事
We swears to do what you wants.
我们对天发誓
We swears.
你发的誓根本不能让我相信
There's no promise you can make that I can trust.
我们发誓...
We swears...
服侍宝物的主人
...to serve the master of the precious.
我愿意对...
We will swear on...
宝物发誓
...on the precious.
咕鲁 咕鲁
Gollum. Gollum.
摩戒是很有魔力的 会迫使你守信的
The Ring is treacherous. It will hold you to your word.
是的
Yes...
神圣的宝物
...on the precious.
On the precious.
我不相信你!
I don't believe you!
- 下来 快下来!     - 山姆!
- Get down! I said, down!     - Sam!
他想要骗我们
He's trying to trick us.
如果我们让他走  他会趁我们熟睡时偷袭我们
If we let him go, he'll throttle us in our sleep.
- 你知道去魔多的路吗?      - 知道
- You know the way to Mordor?     - Yes.
你去过那儿?
You've been there before?
去过
Yes.
你必须带我们到那个黑门
You will lead us to the Black Gate.
到黑门  到黑门!到黑门  主人说了  对!
To the Gate, to the Gate! To the Gate, the master says. Yes!
不行!我们不能去 不去那里 不去他那
No! We won't go back. Not there. Not to him.
他们不能强迫我们 咕鲁!咕鲁!
They can't make us. Gollum! Gollum!
但是我们发誓服侍宝物的主人
But we swore to serve the master of the precious.
不行  那里满天灰烬  炙热如火还有无尽的深渊
No. Ashes and dust and thirst there is, and pits, pits, pits.
还有半兽人  成千上万的半兽人
And Orcses, thousands of Orcses.
邪眼一直在监视着
And always the Great Eye watching, watching.
嘿!快回来!回来!
Hey! Come back now! Come back!
我告诉过你什么
There! What did I tell you?
他跑掉了  那个坏东西
He's run off, the old villain.
他的承诺到此为止了
So much for his promises.
这边  霍比特人
This way, Hobbits.
跟着我!
Follow me!
梅里!
Merry!
你来迟了  我们的主人不耐烦了
You're late. Our master grows impatient.
他现在就想要那些"老鼠"
He wants the Shire-rats now.
我没有从兽人首领那里得到命令
I don't take orders from Orc-maggots.
萨鲁曼会得到他的战利品的
Saruman will have his prize.
我们会负责运送的
We will deliver them.
梅里!
Merry!
梅里! 醒醒
Merry? Wake up.
我的朋友病了
My friend is sick.
他需要水  求求你了
He needs water. Please!
他病了? 给他点药  小伙子们!
Sick, is he? Give him some medicine, boys!
住手
Stop it!
受不了他喝的水?!
Can't take his draught!
- 让他一个人呆着!     - 为什么?
- Leave him alone!     - Why?
你也想来点?
You want some?
那就闭上你的嘴
Then keep your mouth shut.
梅里
Merry.
嗨  皮聘
Hello, Pip.
- 你受伤了     - 我很好
- You're hurt.     - I'm fine.
- 我只是假装     - 假装?
- It was just an act.     - An act?
瞧  我连你也给糊弄了
See? I fooled you too.
别为我担心 皮聘
Don't worry about me, Pippin.
是什么? 你闻到了什么?
What is it? What do you smell?
人的味道
Man-flesh.
他们追上来了
They've picked up our trail.
亚拉冈
Aragorn.
我们快走!
Let's move!
他们加快了脚步
Their pace has quickened.
他们一定是闻到我们了
They must have caught our scent.
快呀!
Hurry!
快呀 金雳
Come on, Gimli!
已经追了三天三夜了
Three days and nights pursuit.
没吃饭 也没休息
No food. No rest.
仍然没有他们的踪迹 但这些坚硬的石头能给什么线索
And no sign of our quarry, but what bare rock can tell.
哈比人的叶形胸针不会无缘无故的掉在这里的
Not idly do the leaves of Lorien fall.
他们可能还活着
They may yet be alive.
离我们只有不到一天路程 来吧
Less than a day ahead of us. Come.
快点 金雳  就快赶上他们了
Come, Gimli! We're gaining on them!
长途跋涉我可最不在行  矮人族是天生短跑健将
I'm wasted on cross-country. We Dwarves are natural sprinters.
但短距离非常危险
Very dangerous over short distances.
洛汗
Rohan.
骠骑之乡
Home of the Horse-lords.
事情有些不对劲
There's something strange at work here.
有些邪恶之物将这里的生物都吓走了
Some evil gives speed to these creatures.
他们想对付我们
Sets its will against us.
勒苟拉斯! 你的精灵之眼能看到什么?
Legolas! What do your Elf-eyes see?
强兽人转往东北方了
The Uruks turn northeast.
他们要将哈比人带到艾辛格
They are taking the Hobbits to Isengard.
萨鲁曼
Saruman.
世界在改变
The world is changing.
现在谁有力量抵挡艾辛格
Who now has the strength to stand against the armies of Isengard...
和魔多大军的攻势?
...and Mordor?
有谁能对抗索伦和萨鲁曼
To stand against the might of Sauron and Saruman...
还有双塔同盟?
...and the union of the two towers?
索伦魔君 我们携手合作
Together, my Lord Sauron...
就能统治整个世界
...we shall rule this Middle-earth.
旧世界将被工业之火吞蚀
The Old World will burn in the fires of Industry.
森林将被夷为平地
The forests will fall.
一股新势力将崛起
A new order will rise.
我们将以半兽人的坚甲利兵
We will drive the machine of war with the sword and the spear...
发动千军万马的进行战争
...and the Iron flsts of the Orc.
我要他们准备好在两周内行军!
I want them armed and ready to march within two weeks!
但是  主人  他们人太多了!
But, my lord, there are too many!
他们没办法按时将他们装备好 我们办不到
They cannot all be armed in time, we don't have the means.
造筑水坝  阻挡河流  修建熔炉
Build a dam, block the stream, work the furnaces night and day.
我们没有足够的燃料来生火
We don't have enough fuel to feed the fires.
法贡森林就在我们门口
The Forest of Fangorn lies on our doorstep.
- 烧了它     - 好的
- Burn it.     - Yes.
我们会为你而战
We will fight for you.
向我发誓
Swear it.
我们愿为萨鲁曼而死
We will die for Saruman.
骠骑国人民强占你们的土地
The Horse-Men took your lands.
他们把你们赶到山上 把你们推下山
They drove your people into the hills to scratch a living off rocks.
凶手!
Murderers!
抢回他们夺去的每一块土地
Take back the lands they stole from you.
烧毁每一个村庄!
Burn every village!
我们只需除掉反抗我们的人
We have only to remove those who oppose us.
洛汗是第一个目标
It will begin in Rohan.
这些农夫一直和你作对
Too long have these peasants stood against you.
但不会再继续了
But no more.
伊欧参! 伊欧参!
Eothain! Eothain!
带着你妹妹 只有两个人会快一点
You take your sister. You'll go faster with just two.
爸爸说伊欧参不能骑加夫
Papa says Eothain must not ride Garulf.
它太高大了
He is too big for him.
听我说  你要骑到伊多拉斯 然后敲响警钟
Listen to me. You must ride to Edoras and raise the alarm.
- 你明白吗?     - 明白 妈妈
- Do you understand me?     - Yes, Mama.
我不想走 我不要走  妈妈
I don't want to leave. I don't want to go, Mama.
斐黛 我会去那里找你们的
Freda, I will find you there.
快去吧
Quickly!
去吧 孩子们
Go, child.
魔君  洛汗国
Rohan, my lord...
洛汗国即将毁灭
...is ready to fall.
史区德
Theodred.
去找王子!
Find the king's son!
- 摩多会为这些付出代价的     - 这些半兽人不是从摩多来的
- Mordor will pay for this.     - These Orcs are not from Mordor.
吾王伊欧墨  这里!
My Lord Eomer, over here!
他还活着
He's alive.
史区德
Theodred.
您的儿子受了重伤
Your son is badly wounded, my lord.
他遭到了半兽人的埋伏
He was ambushed by Orcs.
如果我们不捍卫自己的国家  萨鲁曼就会用武力将其夺走
If we don't defend our country, Saruman will take it by force.
一派胡言
That is a lie.
白袍巫师萨鲁曼是我们的盟友
Saruman the White has ever been our friend and ally.
葛力马
Grima.
半兽人在我国横行霸道
Orcs are roaming freely across our lands.
肆无忌惮地杀人放火
Unchecked. Unchallenged. Killing at will.
他们身上有萨鲁曼的白掌徽记
Orcs bearing the White Hand of Saruman.
你为什么要让国王烦上加烦?
Why do you lay these troubles on an already troubled mind?
你没看到吗?
Can you not see?
你叔叔受够了你的恶行恶状
Your uncle is wearied by your malcontent...
还有你的好勇善斗
...your warmongering.
好勇善斗?
Warmongering?
萨鲁曼买通了你多久?
How long is it since Saruman bought you?
他答应给你什么 葛力马?
What was the promised price, Grima?
等人类死光你就能瓜分财宝?
When all the Men are dead, you will take your share of the treasure?
你窥视我妹妹的美色太久了
Too long have you watched my sister.
我服从你的命令也太久了
Too long have you haunted her steps.
你管的太多了 伊欧墨 伊欧蒙德之子
You see much, Eomer, son of Eomund.
你管太多了
Too much.
你将被驱逐出洛汗国
You are banished forthwith from the kingdom of Rohan...
直到痛苦死去为止
...and all its domains under pain of death.
你在这里没有权力
You have no authority here.
你的命令没用
Your orders mean nothing.
这不是我下达的命令
This order does not come from me.
而是国王下达的
It comes from the king.
他今早发布的命令
He signed it this morning.
呼吸均匀 这是绝窍
Keep breathing. That's the key.
呼吸
Breathe.
他们好像正在被主人鞭打一样狂奔
They've run as if the very whips of their masters were behind them.
我们需要喘口气才能继续走
We're not going no further until we've had a breather.
升起营火!
Get a fire going!
梅里!
Merry!
也许离开夏尔是个错误的决定 皮聘
I think we might have made a mistake leaving the Shire, Pippin.
那是什么声音?
What's making that noise?
那是树的声音
It's the trees.
什么?
What?
你记得雄鹿地边境的老林吗?
You remember the Old Forest, on the borders of Buckland?
传说水中有什么让树木长高
Folk used to say there was something in the water that made the trees grow tall...
然后活起来
...and come alive.
活起来?
Alive?
树木可以
Trees that could whisper...
互相低语
...talk to each other...
甚至走动
...even move.
我饿死了
I'm starving.
是啊 这三天只能吃长满蛆的面包
We ain't had nothing but maggoty bread for three stinking days.
是
Yeah!
为什么我们不来吃点肉?!
Why can't we have some meat?!
吃他们怎么样?
What about them?
他们很新鲜
They're fresh.
他们不是拿来给你们吃的
They are not for eating.
那只吃腿呢?
What about their legs?
反正他们又用不着
They don't need those.
- 看起来很好吃     - 给我滚回去  混蛋
- They look tasty.     - Get back, scum!
这些是给萨鲁曼的囚犯 必须保证他们活着 而且毫发无伤
The prisoners go to Saruman. Alive and unspoiled.
活着的?
Alive?
为什么要活着的? 他们能让我们好好的活动一下吗?
Why alive? Do they give good sport?
他们有东西--一种精灵武器
They have something. An Elvish weapon.
主人的战争需要那东西
The master wants it for the war.
他们认为我们有魔戒
They think we have the Ring.
他们一旦发现我们没有  我们就死定了
As soon as they find out we don't, we're dead.
就只咬一口
Just a mouthful...
来一块腰窝肉
...a bit of the flank.
看起来我们的菜谱上又有肉吃了 小伙子们
Looks like meat's back on the menu, boys.
皮聘
Pippin.
我们快逃
Let's go.
想跑
Go on.
去找援助
Call for help.
尖叫呀!
Squeal.
看现在还有什么能救你
No one's going to save you now.
皮聘!
Pippin!
血红的太阳升起来
A red sun rises.
昨晚一定曾经发生杀戮
Blood has been spilled this night.
洛汗国的骑士
Riders of Rohan...
骠骑国有什么消息?
...what news from the Mark?
一个精灵 一个凡人和一个矮人闯进骠骑国有何贵干?
What business does an Elf, a Man and a Dwarf have in the Riddermark?
快说!
Speak quickly!
骑士 你先报上名来 我就说出我的名字
Give me your name, horse-master, and I shall give you mine.
我一剑砍断你的人头  矮子
I would cut off your head, Dwarf...
要不是你长的那么矮
...if it stood but a little higher from the ground.
你会先一箭毙命
You would die before your stroke fell.
我是亚拉冈 亚拉松之子
I am Aragorn, son of Arathorn.
这是金雳 葛罗音之子  勒苟拉斯 来自幽暗森林
This is Gimli, son of Gloin, and Legolas of the Woodland Realm.
我们是骠骑王希优顿的朋友
We are friends of Rohan and of Theoden, your king.
希优顿已经分不出敌友
Theoden no longer recognizes friend from foe.
他连自家人都认不得
Not even his own kin.
萨尔曼在国王身上下毒
Saruman has poisoned the mind of the king...
将这片土地占为己有
...and claimed lordship over these lands.
我的伙伴们都誓死效忠洛汗国
My company are those loyal to Rohan.
所以才会被放逐
And for that, we are banished.
白袍巫师诡计多端
The White Wizard is cunning.
听说他到处神出鬼没
He walks here and there, they say...
是个身披白色斗蓬的老头
...as an old man hooded and cloaked.
他的爪牙也逃过我们的监视
And everywhere, his spies slip past our nets.
我们不是他派来的间谍
We are no spies.
我们在追赶一群跑向草原西面的强兽人
We track a party of Uruk-hai westward across the plain.
他们抓走我们两个朋友
They have taken two of our friends captive.
我们昨晚歼灭了那伙强兽人
The Uruks are destroyed. We slaughtered them during the night.
但是其中有两个哈比人  你没看见两个哈比人和他们一起吗?
But there were two Hobbits. Did you see two Hobbits with them?
他们身材矮小 在你们眼里像小孩一样
They would be small. Only children to your eyes.
我们没留下活口
We left none alive.
我们把尸体堆起来烧掉
We piled the carcasses and burned them.
他们死了?
Dead?
很遗憾
I am sorry.
哈苏风 阿罗德
Hasufel! Arod!
希望这两匹马能带给你们好运
May these horses bear you to better fortune than their former masters.
后会有期
Farewell.
去找你们的朋友
Look for your friends.
但别心存希望
But do not trust to hope.
我们早已失去希望
It has forsaken these lands.
我们往北走!
We ride north!
这是他们的小腰带
It's one of their wee belts.
我们对不起他们
We failed them.
一个哈比人躺在这儿
A Hobbit lay here.
另一个在这儿
And the other.
他们在地上爬行
They crawled.
而双手被绑住
Their hands were bound.
但他们割断绳索
Their bonds were cut.
然后跑到这里
They ran over here.
有人在追他们
They were followed.
我的腰带!
The belt!
快跑!
Run!
他们的足迹逐渐远离战场
Tracks lead away from the battle...
逃进法贡森林
...into Fangorn Forest.
法贡森林?
Fangorn?
他们疯了么?居然跑进那里
What madness drove them in there?
甩掉他们了吗? 好像甩掉了
Did we lose him? I think we lost him.
我要把你们的心脏给挖出来!
I'm going to rip out your filthy little innards!
过来这里!
Come here!
树!爬到树上去
Trees. Climb a tree.
他已经走了
He's gone.
梅里!
Merry!
我要在你的肚子上戳一个洞!
Let's put a maggot hole in your belly!
快跑呀 梅里!
Run, Merry!
是小半兽人?
Little Orcs.
他在说话 梅里  这棵树在说话
It's talking, Merry. The tree is talking.
树?
Tree?
我不是树
I am no tree!
我是树人
I am an Ent.
守树者
A tree-herder.
森林的守护者
A shepherd of the forest.
别跟他说话  梅里
Don't talk to it, Merry.
别刺激他说话!
Don't encourage it!
有些人叫我树包
Treebeard, some call me.
你站在哪一边?
And whose side are you on?
哪一边?
Side?
我不站在哪一边
I am on nobody's side...
因为没有人站在我这一边  小半兽人
...because nobody's on my side, little Orc.
没有人关心这片森林了
Nobody cares for the woods anymore.
我们不是半兽人 是哈比人!
We're not Orcs! We're Hobbits!
哈比人?
Hobbits?
我没听过哈比人这玩意
Never heard of a Hobbit before.
听起来像是半兽人的幌子!
Sounds like Orc mischief to me!
他们拿着火把
They come with fire.
和斧头闯进来
They come with axes.
又咬又啃  又砍又烧
Gnawing, biting, breaking, hacking, burning!
- 毁灭者  掠夺者! 诅咒他们!     - 不!
- Destroyers and usurpers! Curse them!     - No!
你不明白 我们是哈比人!
You don't understand. We're Hobbits!
半身人!
Halflings!
夏尔人!
Shire-folk!
也许你们是
Maybe you are...
也许不是
...and maybe you aren't.
白袍巫师一定知道
The White Wizard will know.
白袍巫师?
The White Wizard?
萨尔曼
Saruman.
瞧 瞧!
See? See?
我们带你们出来了
We've led you out.
快走呀 哈比人!
Hurry, Hobbitses. Hurry!
我们找到你们真幸运
Very lucky we find you.
好心的哈比人
Nice Hobbit.
这是个沼泽  他把我们带到一片沼泽
It's a bog. He's led us into a swamp.
沼泽 没错
A swamp, yes, yes.
来吧 主人  我们带你穿过迷雾到安全处
Come, master. We will take you on safe paths through the mist.
快啊 哈比人 快
Come, Hobbits! Come! We go quickly.
是我发现的
I found it. I did.
我发现穿过沼泽的路
The way through the marshes.
半兽人不知道 也不会走
Orcs don't use it. Orcs don't know it.
他们都绕一大圈走远路
They go around for miles and miles.
快来吧
Come quickly.
我们必须向影子一样轻而快
Soft and quick as shadows we must be.
我讨厌这地方  太安静了
I hate this place. It's too quiet.
已经两天看不到一只鸟的踪迹了
There's been no sight nor sound of a bird for two days.
不  没有鸟吃
No, no birdses to eat.
没有会吱吱叫的鸟
No crunchable birdses.
我们饿死了!没错!
We are famished! Yes!
我们饿死了  宝物!
Famished we are, precious!
这里
Here.
他在吃什么?
What does it eats?
好吃吗?
Is it tasty?
它会要让我们窒息!
It tries to chokes us!
我们不能吃哈比人食物!
We can't eats Hobbit food!
我们一定会饿死的!
We must starve!
饿死? 正好可以摆脱我们!
Well, starve, then. And good riddance!
噢  残酷的哈比人
Oh, cruel Hobbit.
他不在乎我们饿不饿
It does not care if we be hungry.
不在乎我们死了没
Does not care if we should die.
不像主人
Not like master.
主人在乎
Master cares.
主人知道
Master knows.
没错
Yes.
宝物
Precious.
一旦它完全的支配了我们
Once it takes hold of us...
就永远分不开了
...it never lets go.
不要碰我!
Don't touch me!
那里有死了的东西!
There are dead things!
水里有死人脸
Dead faces in the water.
都死了 都烂掉了
All dead. All rotten.
精灵  人类和半兽人都一样
Elves and Men and Orcses.
很久以前这儿有一场大战
A great battle long ago.
死亡沼泽
Dead Marshes.
没错 没错 这就是它的名字
Yes. Yes, that is their name.
走这边
This way.
别跟着鬼火
Don't follow the lights.
小心 不然哈比人会跌进去成为死亡的一员
Careful now! Or Hobbits go down to join the dead ones...
自己也会点亮一个小小的鬼火
...and light little candles of their own.
佛罗多!
Frodo!
- 咕鲁?     - 别跟着鬼火
- Gollum?     - Don't follow the lights.
- 咕鲁!     - 佛罗多先生!
- Gollum!     - Mr. Frodo!
你没事吧?
Are you all right?
多么金光闪烁!
So bright.
多么美丽啊!
So beautiful.
我们的宝物
Our precious.
你在说什么?
What did you say?
主人应该休息了
Master should be resting.
主人一定要保存体力
Master needs to keep up his strength.
- 你是谁?     - 别问我们 这不关你事
- Who are you?     - Mustn't ask us. Not its business.
咕鲁 咕鲁
Gollum. Gollum.
甘道夫说你曾是住河边的哈比人
Gandalf told me you were one of the river-folk.
我们离乡背井 冰透心 寒彻骨
Cold be heart and hand and bone. Cold be travelers far from home
他说你的一生很悲惨
He said your life was a sad story.
他们没看到在太阳落下 月亮死亡的前面还有什么
They do not see what lies ahead When sun has falled and moon is dead
你和以前的哈比人没有什么区别
You were not so very different from a Hobbit once.
是吗?
Were you?
史麦戈
Smeagol.
你叫我什么?
What did you call me?
那曾经是你的名字 对吧?
That was your name once, wasn't it?
那是很久以前的事了
A long time ago.
我的名字
My name.
史麦戈
Smeagol.
黑骑士!
Black Riders!
快躲! 快躲!
Hide! Hide!
起来 佛罗多  快点!
Come on, Frodo. Come on!
快! 他们会看到我们的! 他们会看到我们的
Quick! They will see us! They will see us!
- 我以为他们死了     - 死?
- I thought they were dead.     - Dead?
不  你是杀不了他们的  不可能
No, you cannot kill them. No.
戒灵!
Wraiths!
骑着飞兽的戒灵!
Wraiths on wings!
他们在召唤它
They are calling for it.
他们在召唤宝物
They are calling for the precious.
佛罗多先生 没事了
Mr. Frodo! It's all right.
我在这儿
I'm here.
快走吧 哈比人
Hurry, Hobbits.
黑门就快到了
The Black Gate is very close.
半兽人的血
Orc blood.
这些足迹很奇怪
These are strange tracks.
这里的空气令人窒息
The air is so close in here.
这座森林很古老
This forest is old.
非常古老
Very old.
充满了记忆
Full of memory...
还有愤怒
...and anger.
这些树在互相交谈
The trees are speaking to each other.
金雳!
Gimli!
把斧子放下来
Lower your ax.
他们有情感  我的朋友
They have feelings, my friend.
是精灵起源
The Elves began it.
叫醒树木 教他们说话
Waking up the trees, teaching them to speak.
会说话的树
Talking trees.
树必须谈些什么?
What do trees have to talk about?
除了松鼠不停的摘果子的事以外
Except the consistency of squirrel droppings.
白袍巫师来了
The White Wizard approaches.
别让他说话 他会对我们下咒
Do not let him speak. He will put a spell on us.
动作要快
We must be quick.
你们在找两个小哈比人
You are tracking the footsteps of two young Hobbits.
他们在哪儿?
Where are they?
他们前天从这里走过
They passed this way the day before yesterday.
他们遇到了你们想不到的人
They met someone they did not expect.
这下你们高兴了?
Does that comfort you?
你是谁?
Who are you?
快现身!
Show yourself!
不可能
It cannot be.
原谅我
Forgive me.
我把你错认为萨鲁曼
I mistook you for Saruman.
我是萨鲁曼
I am Saruman.
或者说是应该是那样子的萨鲁曼
Or rather, Saruman as he should have been.
你跌下去
You fell.
跌入火海
Through fire...
和深水
...and water.
我从最深的地心到最高的山峰
From the lowest dungeon to the highest peak...
和魔尔斯的炎魔展开殊死战
...I fought with the Balrog of Morgoth.
直到我击败强敌
Until at last I threw down my enemy...
把他的尸身丢到山下
...and smote his ruin upon the mountainside.
我被黑暗吞蚀
Darkness took me...
不知道失去意识多久
...and I strayed out of thought and time.
日换星移
Stars wheeled overhead...
每一天都像一辈子一样漫长
...and every day was as long as a life age of the Earth.
但是这并不是终结
But It was not the end.
我终于重获新生
I felt life In me again.
我被送回来
I've been sent back...
完成使命
...until my task is done.
甘道夫?
Gandalf.
Gandalf?
是的
Yes.
以前人家是叫我甘道夫
That was what they used to call me.
灰袍巫师甘道夫
Gandalf the Grey.
那是我以前的名字
That was my name.
甘道夫
Gandalf.
我现在是白袍巫师甘道夫
I am Gandalf the White.
我在危急时刻回来帮助你们
And I come back to you now...
来扭转乾坤
...at the turn of the tide.
你们的旅程开启了全新的一页
One stage of your journey is over. Another begins.
- 我们必须尽快赶到伊多拉斯     - 伊多拉斯?
- We must travel to Edoras with all speed.     - Edoras?
这段路可不短!
That is no short distance!
我们听说洛汗国出事了  国王生病了
We hear of trouble in Rohan. It goes ill with the king.
是的  而且病得很重
Yes, and it will not be easily cured.
那我们要白跑一趟了?
Then we have run all this way for nothing?
我们要把那些可怜的小矮人留在这
Are we to leave those poor Hobbits here...
可怕  漆黑而又阴冷的树林里?
...in this horrid, dark, dank tree-infested...?
我指的是这迷人的
I mean, charming...
非常迷人的森林
...quite charming forest.
我们只有一点点机会把梅里和皮聘带到法贡森林去
It was more than mere chance that brought Merry and Pippin to Fangorn.
一种很强大的力量已经在这里沉睡了很多年
A great power has been sleeping here for many long years.
梅里和皮聘的到来就像一块小石子的滑落
The coming of Merry and Pippin will be like the falling of small stones...
会引发山里的大雪崩
...that starts an avalanche in the mountains.
有一件事你还没改变  亲爱的朋友
In one thing you have not changed, dear friend.
你还是爱打谜
You still speak in riddles.
一件事情就要发生  但是自古以来一直还没有发生
A thing is about to happen that has not happened since the Elder Days.
树人们就要醒来了
The Ents are going to wake up...
- 而且会发现他们很强大     - 强大?!
- and find that they are strong.     - Strong?!
哦  这可不错
Oh, that's good.
所以不要焦虑  矮人主人
So stop your fretting, Master Dwarf.
梅里和皮聘非常安全
Merry and Pippin are quite safe.
事实上  他们比你要安全得多
In fact, they are far safer than you are about to be.
这个新的甘道夫比老的要暴躁得多
This new Gandalf's more grumpy than the old one.
它是一匹米亚拉斯神驹
That is one of the Mearas...
除非我的双眼被符咒迷惑
...unless my eyes are cheated by some spell.
它是影疾
Shadowfax.
它是马中之王
He is the lord of all horses...
跟我一起经历了很多危险
...and has been my friend through many dangers.
哦  我的山犁花
Orowan mine
我见到你闪耀
I saw you shine
在一个炎炎夏日
Upon a summer's day
在你的头上高高戴着的皇冠
Upon your head How golden-red
是多么的金红
The crown you bore aloft
美丽的诗句
Such a beautiful verse.
- 更远了吗?      - 不要匆忙
- Is it much further?     - Bru-ra-hroom. Don't be hasty.
也许你可以称它为远
You might call it far, perhaps.
我的家在森林深处
My home lies deep in the forest...
靠近山脚的地方
...near the roots of the mountain.
我答应甘道夫保护你们安全
I told Gandalf I would keep you safe.
我一定会好好保护你们
And safe is where I'll keep you.
我相信你们也会喜欢下一个的
I believe you will enjoy this next one too.
是我自己的作品
It's one of my own compositions.
没错
Right.
在沉睡的树叶铺盖的屋顶下
Beneath the roof of sleeping leaves
在那张开的树木的梦里
And the dreams of trees unfold
当森林的殿堂荫绿清凉的时候
When woodland halls are green and cool
当风儿向西吹的时候
And the wind is In the West
回到我身边
Come back to me
说我的土地是最好的
And say my land is best
睡吧  小夏尔
Sleep, little Shirelings.
不要理会夜晚的声音
Heed no nightly noise.
一直睡到清晨
Sleep till morning light.
我有事要去森林里
I have business in the forest.
要叫许多人  许多人必须来
There are many to call. Many that must come.
阴影对法贡森林的事撒谎了
The Shadow lies on Fangorn.
树林的枯萎越来越近了
The withering of all woods is drawing near.
东部怒目而视的影子不断发展
The veiling shadow that glowers in the east takes shape.
所罗会因为没有对手而痛苦
Sauron will suffer no rival.
从巴拉多的顶锋他不断地观望着
From the summit of Barad-dur, his Eye watches ceaselessly.
但是他还不是最强大的人  以至无所畏惧
But he is not so mighty yet that he is above fear.
疑惑一直侵蚀着他
Doubt ever gnaws at him.
谣言已经传到他那里
The rumor has reached him.
努曼诺尔的后嗣依然活着
The heir of Numenor still lives.
所罗害怕你  亚拉冈
Sauron fears you, Aragorn.
他害怕你将成为的人物
He fears what you may become.
所以他会快速而且猛烈地打击人类世界
And so he'll strike hard and fast at the world of Men.
他会利用他的傀儡萨鲁曼来毁灭洛汗国
He will use his puppet Saruman to destroy Rohan.
战争就要降临了
War is coming.
洛汗国必须保卫自己  我们为洛汗国的挑战
Rohan must defend itself, and therein lies our first challenge...
是弱小的  我们准备好牺牲了
...for Rohan is weak and ready to fall.
国王的思想被束缚了  他只是一个萨鲁曼老装置了
The king's mind is enslaved, it's an old device of Saruman's.
他现在对国王希优顿控制非常强
His hold over King Theoden is now very strong.
所罗和萨鲁曼正在勒紧绳索
Sauron and Saruman are tightening the noose.
但是对于他们所有的诡计
But for all their cunning...
我们还有一个优势
...we have one advantage.
就是魔戒仍然隐藏着
The Ring remains hidden.
所以我们应该找到并毁灭它
And that we should seek to destroy it...
还没有进入他们最黑暗的梦境
...has not yet entered their darkest dreams.
所以哈比人拿着敌人的武器正在向魔多进发
And so the weapon of the enemy is moving towards Mordor in the hands of a Hobbit.
离末日山一天天逼近
Each day brings it closer to the fires of Mount Doom.
现在我们必须相信佛罗多
We must trust now in Frodo.
一切取决于速度
Everything depends upon speed...
还需对他的要求保守秘密
...and the secrecy of his quest.
你不要后悔做出留下他的决定
Do not regret your decision to leave him.
佛罗多必须独自完成这个任务
Frodo must finish this task alone.
他并不是一个人
He's not alone.
山姆跟着他
Sam went with him.
真的吗?
Did he?
真是这样? 太好了
Did he, indeed? Good.
对  非常好
Yes, very good.
魔多的黑门
The Black Gate of Mordor.
我的天
Oh, save us.
如果我老爸现在看到我们一定会说上两句的
My old Gaffer would have a thing or two to say if he could see us now.
主人要我带他到魔多
Master says to show him the way into Mordor.
史麦戈就乖乖带主人去
So good Smeagol does, master says so.
我是这样做的
I did.
没错
That's it, then.
我们闯不进去
We can't get past that.
看!
Look!
你看城门
The gate.
它打开了!
It's opening!
我能看见下面的路
I can see a way down.
山姆 不!
Sam, no!
主人!
Master!
- 我并没有要你跟我进去  山姆     - 我知道  佛罗多先生
- I do not ask you to come with me, Sam.     - I know, Mr. Frodo.
我怀疑到里面披精灵斗蓬也没有用
I doubt even these Elvish cloaks will hide us in there.
- 去吧!     - 不!
- Now!      - No!
不行 主人!
No! No, master!
他们会抓到你的! 他们会抓到你的!
They catch you! They catch you!
别把它交给他了
Don't take it to him.
他想要宝贝
He wants the precious.
他一直在找它
Always he is looking for it.
宝贝也想回到他手上
And the precious is wanting to go back to him.
但是我们不能让他拿去
But we mustn't let him have it.
不行 有另一条路
No! There's another way.
更隐密  更黑暗的路
More secret. A dark way.
- 你为什么不早说?     - 因为主人没有问
- Why haven't you spoken of this before?     - Because master did not ask.
他在动歪脑筋
He's up to something.
你是说有另一条路到魔多?
Are you saying there's another way into Mordor?
对 有一条小路
Yes. There's a path...
和一些阶梯
...and some stairs.
然后
And then...
有一条隧道
...a tunnel.
他都带我们到这儿了  山姆
He's led us this far, Sam.
佛罗多先生 不行
Mr. Frodo, no.
他信守他的诺言
He's been true to his word.
不要
No.
带路吧 史麦戈
Lead the way, Smeagol.
史麦戈总是很乐意帮忙
Good Smeagol always helps.
喂?
Hello?
树须?
Treebeard?
他去哪了?
Where has he gone?
昨天晚上我做了一个最美妙的梦
I had the loveliest dream last night.
那有一个大桶  里面装满了烟叶
There was this large barrel, full of pipe-weed.
我们痛痛快快的抽完这些烟叶  然后
And we smoked all of it. And then...
你不舒服了
...you were sick.
只要能抽上一口老雪茄  要我干啥都行
I'd give anything for a whiff of Old Toby.
你听到这个了吗?
Did you hear that?
又来了
There it is again.
这里有什么不对劲  完全不对劲
Something's not right here. Not right at all.
你只是说有些东西像树
You just said something... Treeish.
不  我没有  我只是在伸展
No, I didn't. I was just stretching.
你变高了
You're taller.
- 谁?     - 你!
- Who?      - You!
- 比什么?     - 比我!
- Than what?      - Than me!
我一直比你高
I've always been taller than you.
皮聘  谁都知道我比较高  而你比较矮
Pippin, everyone knows I'm the tall one. You're the short one.
行了  梅里
Please, Merry.
你多高? 三英尺六英寸? 最多?
You're what? Three-foot-six? At the most?
然而我有差不多三英尺七英寸
Whereas me, I'm pushing 3'7".
三英尺八英寸!
3'8"!
三英尺八英寸
Three-foot-eight.
你做了些什么
You did something.
梅里  不要! 不要喝
Merry, don't! Don't drink it!
梅里!
Merry!
不 树须说你不应该喝
No, Treebeard said that you shouldn't have any.
- 我想喝!     - 这可能很危险!
- I want some!     - It could well be dangerous!
给我  梅里!
Give me it back. Merry!
发生什么事了?!
What's happening?!
它抓住我的腿了!
It's got my leg!
梅里!
Merry!
救命!
Help!
跟你一起走
Away with you.
你不应该醒
You should not be waking.
吃土  挖深点  喝点水
Eat earth. Dig deep. Drink water.
去睡觉
Go to sleep.
跟你一起
Away with you.
快点  森林就要醒了
Come, the forest is waking up.
它很危险
It isn't safe.
这些树疯了  很危险
The trees have grown wild and dangerous.
愤怒吞噬了他们的心
Anger festers in their hearts.
他们的思想邪恶
Black are their thoughts.
仇恨强烈
Strong is their hate.
如果他们能伤害你们  他们就会这么干
They will harm you if they can.
我们现在人手太少
There are too few of us now.
人太少不能对付他们
Too few of us Ents left to manage them.
为什么你们能活这么长而人却这么少?
Why are there so few of you when you have lived so long?
- 树人有孩子吗?     -布-拉-鲁
- Are there Ent children?     - Bru-ra-hroom.
已经很多很多年没有了
There have been no Entings for a terrible long count of years.
- 为什么这样?     - 我们失去了树人妻子
- Why is that?     - We lost the Entwives.
哦  真遗憾
Oh, I'm sorry.
- 她们怎么死的?     - 死? 不
- How did they die?     - Die? No.
我们把她们弄丢了
We lost them.
到现在还找不到她们
And now we cannot find them.
我想你们在夏尔没有看到树人妻子吧?
I don't suppose you've seen Entwives in the Shire?
应该没有
Can't say that I have.
你  皮聘?
You, Pip?
她们看起来像什么?
What do they look like?
现在我已经记不清了
I don't remember now.
伊多拉斯以及梅杜西金殿
Edoras and the Golden Hall of Meduseld.
洛汗国国王希优顿的皇宫
There dwells Theoden, King of Rohan...
他的身心受到蛊惑
...whose mind is overthrown.
萨鲁曼控制了希优顿
Saruman 's hold over King Theoden Is now very strong.
王上 您的儿子
My lord, your son...
他死了
...he is dead.
王上?
My lord?
叔叔?
Uncle?
您不去看他?
Will you not go to him?
您什么也不做吗?
Will you do nothing?
谨言慎行
Be careful what you say.
我们在这不受欢迎
Do not look for welcome here.
他一定是昨晚去世的
Oh, he must have died sometime in the night.
国王失去独子和王储真不幸
What a tragedy for the king to lose his only son and heir.
我理解  他的死一定让你很难过
I understand. His passing is hard to accept.
尤其是你的兄长也弃你不顾
Especially now that your brother has deserted you.
让我一个人静一静 毒蛇!
Leave me alone, snake!
你的确是孤零零的一个人
Oh, but you are alone.
天晓得你在黑暗中受多少煎熬
Who knows what you've spoken to the darkness...
你在孤寂难熬的夜晚
...in the bitter watches of the night...
生命一点一滴地凋谢枯萎
...when all your life seems to shrink.
你受到四面高墙禁锢
The walls of your bower closing in about you.
如同笼中鸟一般渴望自由
A hutch to trammel some wild thing in.
这么美丽
So fair.
却如此冷漠
So cold.
就像寒冬后的春泉依然冰冷
Like a morning of pale spring still clinging to winter's chill.
你的话是毒药
Your words are poison.
连墓园都比这儿热闹
You'll find more cheer in a graveyard.
你们不能带武器见希优顿王  灰袍甘道夫
I cannot allow you before Theoden King so armed, Gandalf Greyhame.
这是葛力马巧言之令
By order of Grima Wormtongue.
你的手杖
Your staff.
你就让一个老人带着手杖吧
You would not part an old man from his walking stick.
王上 灰袍甘道夫来了
My lord, Gandalf the Grey is coming.
他是恶兆的信差
He's a herald of woe.
你近来似乎不太欢迎来访者
The courtesy of your hall is somewhat lessened of late...
希优顿王
...Theoden King.
他是不受欢迎的
He's not welcome.
我为什么要欢迎你?
Why should I welcome you...
乌鸦嘴甘道夫?
...Gandalf Stormcrow?
说得好 王上
A just question, my liege.
这名江湖术士这么晚才跑来
Late is the hour in which this conjurer chooses to appear.
我替他取名为噩耗
Lathspell I name him.
噩耗就是不受欢迎的恶客
Ill news is an ill guest.
给我闭嘴  别在这儿搬弄是非
Be silent. Keep your forked tongue behind your teeth.
我通过烈火和死亡的试炼
I have not passed through fire and death...
不是为了跟蠢材做口舌之争
...to bandy crooked words with a witless worm.
他的手杖
His staff.
我叫你们没收巫师的手杖
I told you to take the wizard's staff.
希优顿
Theoden...
塞哲尔之子
...son of Thengel...
你活在阴影下太久了
...too long have you sat in the Shadows.
你最好乖乖别动
I would stay still if I were you.
听我说
Hearken to me!
我把你从咒语中释放出来
I release you from the spell.
你在这里没有力量
You have no power here...
灰袍甘道夫
...Gandalf the Grey.
萨鲁曼 我要把你逼出来  就像把剧毒逼出伤口
I will draw you, Saruman, as poison is drawn from a wound.
等等
Wait.
我一走 希优顿就会死
If I go, Theoden dies.
你杀不了我
You did not kill me...
更杀不了他
...you will not kill him.
洛汗国是我的
Rohan is mine.
出来
Be gone.
你很面熟
I know your face.
伊欧玟
Eowyn.
甘道夫
Gandalf?
你又重获自由了 我的朋友
Breathe the free air again, my friend.
我的梦里充满了黑暗
Dark have been my dreams of late.
你从前的力量会恢复的
Your fingers would remember their old strength better...
只要你握住宝剑
...if they grasped your sword.
我只想
I've only...
自始至终只想服侍您  王上
...ever served you, my lord.
你只想用邪术让我臣服于你
Your leechcraft would have had me crawling on all fours like a beast!
请放逐我吧
Send me not from your sight.
不 王上 饶了他吧
No, my lord! No, my lord.
让他走
Let him go.
已经流了太多血了
Enough blood has been spilt on his account.
给我滚开!
Get out of my way!
希优顿王万岁!
Hail, Theoden King!
希优德呢?
Where is Theodred?
我儿子呢?
Where is my son?
永志花
Simbelmyn?
它一直生长在先王的坟上
Ever has it grown on the tombs of my forebearers.
现在也将永远覆盖在吾儿之墓
Now it shall cover the grave of my son.
厄运应该降临在我身上
Alas that these evil days should be mine.
少年英年早逝 老人苟延残喘
The young perish and the old linger.
但我还是该活着
That I should live...
看着我的王国灭亡
...to see the last days of my house.
希优德的死不是你的错
Theodred's death was not of your making.
白发人不该送黑发人
No parent should have to bury their child.
他生前很坚强
He was strong in life.
死后也将与你的先王同在
His spirit will find its way to the halls of your fathers.
他们措手不及
They had no warning.
手无寸铁
They were unarmed.
现在野人正穿越西谷  烧毁经过的一切
Now the Wild Men are moving through the Westfold, burning as they go.
干草  茅屋和树木
Rick, cot and tree.
妈妈呢?
Where is Mama?
这只是萨鲁曼大军的一小部份
This is but a taste of the terror that Saruman will unleash.
他和索伦结盟后势力更强大
All the more potent for he is driven now by fear of Sauron.
你必须正面迎敌
Ride out and meet him head on.
引开他的大军 保护老弱妇孺
Draw him away from your women and children.
你一定要迎战
You must fight.
目前有两千名精兵向北而来
You have 2000 good men riding north as we speak.
伊欧墨对你忠心耿耿
Eomer is loyal to you.
他的部下会回来为他们的国王奋战
His men will return and fight for their king.
他们离这儿有三百里路
They will be 300 leagues from here by now.
伊欧墨救不了我们
Eomer cannot help us.
我知道你要我怎么做
I know what it is you want of me...
但是我不能让我的人民白白去送死
...but I will not bring further death to my people.
我不想冒险全面开战
I will not risk open war.
敌人已向你宣战  不管你想不想冒险
Open war is upon you, whether you would risk it or not.
就我所知
When last I looked...
我希优顿才是洛汗国国王  不是亚拉冈
...Theoden, not Aragorn, was king of Rohan.
国王的命令是什么
Then what is the king's decision?
国王下令
By order of the king...
全城军民撤退
...the city must empty.
撤退到圣盔谷碉堡
We make for the refuge of Helm's Deep.
不要携带笨重的财宝只带必需品
Do not burden yourself with treasures. Take only what provisions you need.
圣盔谷
Helm's Deep.
他应该一决死战 而不是逃之夭夭
They flee to the mountains when they should stand and fight.
一国之君就应该捍卫人民
Who will defend them if not their king?
他这么做也是为了人民着想
He's only doing what he thinks is best for his people.
圣盔谷以前救过他们一命
Helm's Deep has saved them in the past.
那道峡谷无路可退  希优顿这是自寻死路
There is no way out of that ravine. Theoden is walking into a trap.
他认为他们在那儿很安全
He thinks he's leading them to safety.
但是他们会惨遭屠杀
What they will get is a massacre.
希优顿很固执 我替他担忧
Theoden has a strong will, but I fear for him.
我也担心洛汗国将灭亡
I fear for the survival of Rohan.
亚拉冈 他需要你的帮助
He will need you before the end, Aragorn.
洛汗国人民也需要你
The people of Rohan will need you.
你们要挡住敌人的攻势
The defenses have to hold.
一定挡得住
They will hold.
灰袍圣徒
The Grey Pilgrim.
他们以前都这么叫我
That's what they used to call me.
我在世上活了三百辈子  现在的时间却不够用
Three hundred lives of Men I've walked this earth, and now I have no time.
希望我能找到救兵
With luck, my search will not be in vain.
五天后等待我的出现
Look to my coming at first light on the fifth day.
黎明时向东方看
At dawn, look to the east.
去吧
Go.
这匹马快疯了  王上  你拿他没有办法，算了吧
That horse is half mad, my lord. There's nothing you can do. Leave him.
他的名字是布理哥
His name is Brego.
他是我堂兄的马
He was my cousin's horse.
布理哥
Brego.
我听说过矮人们的魔法
I have heard of the magic of Elves...
但是我没有从北边找
...but I did not look for it in a Ranger from the North.
你说话就像他们自己一样
You speak as one of their own.
我在乌丘生活了
I was raised in Rivendell...
一段时间
...for a time.
把他放了
Turn this fellow free.
他已经看够了战争
He's seen enough of war.
白袍甘道夫!
Gandalf the White.
笨蛋甘道夫!
Gandalf the Fool!
他是想用他的新行头侮辱我吧?
Does he seek to humble me with his newfound piety?
有三个人追随这个男巫
There were three who followed the wizard.
一个精灵  一个矮人还有一个人
An Elf, a Dwarf and a Man.
你这个恶心的家伙
You stink of horse.
这个男人
The Man...
- 是从刚铎来的吗?     - 不是  从北边来的
- ...was he from Gondor?     - No, from the North.
我想他是一个登丹巡逻骑兵
One of the Dunedain Rangers, I thought he was.
他的衣服很破旧
His cloth was poor.
而且他戴着一个奇怪的指环
And yet he bore a strange ring.
两个眼睛绿色的阴险家伙
Two serpents with emerald eyes.
一个狼吞虎咽  另一个戴着金色花朵的王冠
One devouring, the other crowned with golden flowers.
巴拉汉的指环
The Ring of Barahir.
所以灰袍巫師甘道夫认为他已经找到了埃西铎的后裔
So Gandalf Greyhame thinks he has found Isildur's heir.
刚铎失去的国王  他是个傻瓜
The lost king of Gondor. He is a fool.
香火已经断了很多年了
The line was broken years ago.
没什么关系
It matters not.
人类世界应该灭亡
The world of Men shall fall.
这会从伊多拉斯开始
It will begin at Edoras.
我准备好了  加姆林
I am ready, Gamling.
备马
Bring my horse.
这不算一次失败
This is not a defeat.
我们会回来的
We will return.
你的剑法不错
You have some skill with a blade.
这个国家的女人很早就懂得
Women of this country learned long ago
不会用剑就死于剑下
Those without swords can still die upon them.
我不怕死也不怕痛
I fear neither death nor pain.
那么你怕什么?
What do you fear, my lady?
被困在牢笼里
A cage.
直到老死才接受这个命运
To stay behind bars until use and old age accept them.
没有机会证明我的英勇
And all chance of valor has gone beyond recall or desire.
你是公主
You're a daughter of kings...
也是洛汗国的骠骑女战士
...a shieldmaiden of Rohan.
那不会是你的命运
I do not think that would be your fate.
希优顿不会留在伊多拉斯
Theoden will not stay at Edoras.
他很清楚那儿不安全
It's vulnerable. He knows this.
他知道王都将受到攻击
He will expect an attack on the city.
他们会逃到圣盔谷
They will flee to Helm's Deep...
洛汗国的堡垒
...the great fortress of Rohan.
前往圣盔谷的山路崎岖危险
It Is a dangerous road to take through the mountains.
前进速度会很缓慢
They will be slow.
他们当中也会有老弱妇孺
They will have women and children with them.
派出狼骑士
Send out your Warg-riders.
嘿  臭东西  别走得太远
Hey, stinker, don't go getting too far ahead.
- 你为什么那样?     - 怎样?
- Why do you do that?     - What?
一直骂他 不断找他碴
Call him names. Run him down all the time.
因为
Because.
因为他很坏 弗罗多
Because that's what he is, Mr. Frodo.
他只会说谎和骗人
There's naught left in him but lies and deceit.
他想要魔戒，他只在乎魔戒
It's the Ring he wants.  It's all he cares about.
你不知道魔戒对他的折磨
You have no idea what it did to him...
到现在还在折磨他
...what it's still doing to him.
我想要帮助他
I want to help him, Sam.
为什么?
Why?
因为我必须相信他会变好
Because I have to believe he can come back.
你救不了他的
You can't save him, Mr. Frodo.
你知道什么? 你什么都不知道!
What do you know about it? Nothing!
对不起 山姆  我不知道我怎么了
I'm sorry, Sam. I don't know why I said that.
我知道
I do.
都是因为魔戒
It's the Ring.
你的视线离不开它
You can't take your eyes off it.
我看到你
I've seen you.
你不吃不喝不睡觉
You're not eating. You barely sleep.
它控制了你
It's taken hold of you, Mr. Frodo.
- 你一定要反抗     - 我知道我该做什么
- You have to fight it.     - I know what I have to do, Sam.
魔戒信任我  这是我的使命
The Ring was entrusted to me. It's my task.
我的!我一个人的!
Mine! My own!
你听听你自己
Can't you hear yourself?
你知道你像谁吗?
Don't you know who you sound like?
我们需要它
We wants it.
We needs it.
一定要得到宝贝
Must have the precious.
他们都从我们身上把它偷走
They stole it from us.
鬼鬼祟祟的小哈比人
Sneaky little Hobbitses.
奸诈狡猾  虚伪做作
Wicked. Tricksy. False.
不 主人不是
No. Not master.
才怪 他最虚伪了
Yes, precious. False.
他们会说谎骗你  伤害你
They will cheat you, hurt you, lie!
主人是我的朋友
Master's my friend.
你没有朋友  没有人喜欢你
You don't have any friends. Nobody likes you.
不听 我不听
Not listening. I'm not listening.
你是个骗子 小偷
You're a liar and a thief.
不是
No.
杀人凶手
Murderer.
走开
Go away.
走开?
Go away?
我恨你
I hate you.
没有我哪会有你? 咕鲁  咕鲁
Where would you be without me? Gollum. Gollum.
我救了我们
I saved us.
都是我的功劳  都是因为我大家才能活命
It was me. We survived because of me.
我现在不必靠你了
Not anymore.
你说什么?
What did you say?
主人会照顾我们
Master looks after us now.
我们不需要你
We don't need you.
什么?
What?
你走吧
Leave now...
别再回来
...and never come back.
不
No.
快走 别再回来
Leave now and never come back.
Leave now and never come back!
我们叫他走
We told him to go away.
他就走了 宝贝
And away he goes, precious.
他走了! 他走了! 他走了!
Gone! Gone! Gone!
史麦戈自由了
Smeagol is free!
你瞧
Look.
你看史麦戈找到什么?
Look. See what Smeagol finds?
它们还小
They are young.
它们很新鲜 肉也很嫩
They are tender. They are nice.
没错 快吃了它们吧
Yes, they are. Eat them. Eat them!
你这样做只会让他恶心
You'll make him sick, you will behaving like that.
兔肉只有一种煮法
There's only one way to eat a brace of coneys.
你在干嘛
What's it doing?
又蠢又肥的哈比人
Stupid, fat Hobbit.
你糟蹋了兔肉
It ruins it.
哪里会? 这样最好吃了
What's to ruin? There's hardly any meat on them.
如果来点洋芋就更棒
What we need is a few good taters.
洋芋是什么东西?
What's taters, precious?
洋芋是什么?
What's taters? Eh?
就是马铃薯
Po-ta-toes.
煮成洋芋泥 跟肉一起炖
Boil them, mash them, stick them in a stew.
或是炸成金黄色的洋芋片  配一块酥脆的炸鱼
Lovely, big, golden chips with a nice piece of fried fish.
连你都无法抗拒
Even you couldn't say no to that.
我们当然可以抗拒
Oh, yes, we could.
白白地糟蹋一条鲜鱼
Spoil a nice fish.
活蹦乱跳的生鱼
Give it to us raw and wriggling.
你自己吃臭洋芋片吧
You keep nasty chips.
你真是没救
You're hopeless.
佛罗多先生?
Mr. Frodo?
- 他们是谁?     - 坏蛋
- Who are they?     - Wicked Men.
索伦的爪牙
Servants of Sauron.
他们被叫到魔多
They are called to Mordor.
黑暗魔君在聚集邪恶大军
The Dark One is gathering all armies to him.
要不了多久  他很快就会准备好
It won't be long now. He will soon be ready.
- 准备做什么?     - 展开大战
- Ready to do what?     - To make his war.
最后一场大战让黑暗笼罩大地
The last war that will cover all the world in Shadow.
我们得赶路 来吧 山姆
We've got to get moving. Come on, Sam.
佛罗多先生!
Mr. Frodo.
你看
Look.
那是猛玛
It's an oliphaunt.
老家的人绝对不会相信
No one at home will believe this.
史麦戈?
Smeagol?
我们逗留太久了
We've lingered here too long.
走吧 山姆
Come on, Sam.
等等!我们是无辜的旅行者!
Wait! We're innocent travelers!
这里不会有旅行者的  只可能有邪黑塔的爪牙
There are no travelers in this land. Only servants of the Dark Tower.
我们要干一件秘密的差事
We are bound to an errand of secrecy.
那些宣称要反对敌人的家伙会尽力不妨碍我们
Those that claim to oppose the enemy would do well not to hinder us.
敌人?
The enemy?
我认为  他的责任感不亚于你
His sense of duty was no less than yours, I deem.
你奇怪他的名字是
You wonder what his name is...
来自他的出生之地
...where he came from.
如果他本质真的邪恶的话
And if he was really evil at heart.
那是什么欺骗和威胁能让他背井离乡呢
What lies or threats led him on this long march from home.
如果他想安详地呆在那里
If he would not rather have stayed there in peace.
我们全都会在战争中死掉
War will make corpses of us all.
把他们捆起来
Bind their hands.
没错 女矮人是很少见
It's true, you don't see many Dwarf women.
老实说  她们的长相和声音
And in fact, they are so alike in voice and appearance...
常常被误认为是男矮人
...that they're often mistaken for Dwarf men.
胡子先生
It's the beards.
甚至有人相信
This, in turn, has given rise to the belief...
根本没有女矮人
...that there are no Dwarf women...
矮人都是从地洞蹦出来的
...and that Dwarves just spring out of holes in the ground...
这当然是无稽之谈
...which is, of course, ridiculous.
我没事 别紧张
It's all right. Nobody panic.
我是故意凸槌的
That was deliberate. It was deliberate.
我很久没见我侄女笑过了
I haven't seen my niece smile for a long time.
她父亲的尸体被带回来的时候  她还是个孩子
She was a girl when they brought her father back dead.
被兽人杀了
Cut down by Orcs.
她看着她母亲悲痛欲绝
She watched her mother succumb to grief.
只留下她孤单一人活在恐惧中还要照顾她的国王
Then she was left alone, to tend her king in growing fear.
命中注定要等待一个会像父亲一样疼爱她的人
Doomed to wait upon an old man who should have loved her as a father.
金雳
Gimli.
不  我不能
No, I couldn't
我真的不能
I really couldn't.
我做了些炖肉
I made some stew.
不是很多  不过是热的
It isn't much, but it's hot.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 很好吃     - 真的?
- It's good.     - Really?
叔叔告诉了我一些奇怪的事情
My uncle told me a strange thing.
他说你和我祖父塞哲尔一起战斗
He said that you rode to war with Thengel, my grandfather.
但我认为他错了
But he must be mistaken.
希优顿王的记忆很好  那时候他还是个孩子
King Theoden has a good memory. He was only a small child at the time.
而你至少有60岁
Then you must be at least 60.
70?
Seventy?
不会是80!
But you cannot be 80!
Eighty-seven.
你是登丹人
You are one of the Dunedain.
努曼诺尔的后代  会很长寿
A descendant of Numenor, blessed with long life.
据说你的经历带有传奇色彩
It was said that your race had passed into legend.
我们当中很少人活了下来
There are few of us left.
北方王国很久以前就被摧毁了
The Northern Kingdom was destroyed long ago.
对不起  吃吧
I'm sorry. Please, eat.
暮星的光芒不会减弱
The light of the Evenstar does not wax and wane.
我想要给谁就给谁
It is mine to give to whom I will.
就像我的心一样
Like my heart.
快睡吧
Go to sleep.
我已经睡着了
I am asleep.
这只是个梦
This is a dream.
那么这一定是美梦
Then it is a good dream.
睡吧
Sleep.
你曾经说过...
"Minlû pedich nin..."
该来的终会来的
"i aur hen telitha."
这不是结束...这只是开始
"ú i vethed na i onnad."
你必须跟随佛罗多
"Boe bedich go Frodo."
那是你的宿命
"Han bâd lîn."
我看不见我的宿命
"Dolen i vad o nin."
它就在你脚下
"Si peliannen i vâd na dail lîn."
你没法逃避
"Siboe ú-dhannathach."
亚文
Arwen...
如果你什么都不信...
"Ae ú-esteliach nad..."
就相信这个吧
"estelio han."
相信我们
"estelio ammen."
她在哪里?
Where is she?
给你那枚宝石的女人
The woman who gave you that jewel.
我们的时代结束了
Our time here is ending.
亚玟也要离开
Arwen's time is ending.
让她走吧
Let her go.
让她坐船前往西方
Let her take the ship into the west.
让她带着对你的爱到海外仙境
Let her bear away her love for you to the Undying Lands.
她对你的爱将永远长青
There it will be ever green.
但是她只有回忆
But never more than memory.
我不会让我女儿留下来等死
I will not leave my daughter here to die.
- 她心存希望才会留下来的    - 她是为了你才留下来
- She stays because she still has hope.   - She stays for you.
她应该跟她的族人在一起
She belongs with her people.
你为什么要我走?
Why are you saying this?
我是凡人 你是精灵
I am mortal. You are Elf-kind.
这只是一场梦
It was a dream, Arwen.
一场美梦而已
Nothing more.
真不敢相信
I don't believe you.
这属于你
This belongs to you.
这是送你的礼物
It was a gift.
留着它
Keep it.
大人?
My lord?
她要跟其他的精灵到海外仙境
She is sailing to the Undying Lands with all that is left of her kin.
怎么了?
What is it?
-哈玛?      - 我不确定
- Hama?     - I'm not sure.
狼骑士!
Wargs!
他是来探路的先锋!
A scout!
- 怎么了? 那是什么?     - 狼骑士 我们受到攻击!
- What is it? What do you see?    - Warg! We're under attack!
带他们离开这里!
Get them out of here!
骑士全都到前锋!
All riders to the head of the column.
快让我上去 我也是骑士
Come on. Get me up here. I'm a rider.
来吧!
Come on!
快带人民到圣盔谷 快去!
You must lead the people to Helm's Deep, and make haste.
- 我可以作战      - 不行!
- I can fight.     - No!
你要为了我带他们去
You must do this, for me.
跟我来!
Follow me!
- 前进 我是说向前冲     - 快到低地
- Forward. I mean, charge forward.   - Make for the lower ground!
- 很好 快呀     - 聚在一起
- That's it! Go on!     - Stay together!
快来领死吧
Bring your pretty face to my ax.
那一只算我的
That one counts as mine!
臭东西
Stinking creature.
亚拉冈!
Aragorn!
亚拉冈?
Aragorn?
快说我就让你死得痛快
Tell me what happened and I will ease your passing.
他...
He's...
死了
...dead.
他跌下悬崖
He took a little tumble off the cliff.
你说谎
You lie.
把伤者放到马背上
Get the wounded on horses.
艾辛格的恶狼会再回来
The wolves of Isengard will return.
把死者留下来
Leave the dead.
来吧
Come.
- 终于到了!     - 圣盔谷!
- At last!     - Helm's Deep.
到了 圣盔谷
There it is, Helm's Deep.
我们安全了
We're safe!
安全了 王女
We're safe, my lady.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 妈妈     - 伊欧参!
- Mama!     - Eothain!
弗雷达!
Freda!
- 剩下的在哪儿?     - 只有这些了  女王
- Where is the rest?   - This is all we could save, my lady.
拿到洞里去
Take it to the caves.
给国王让路
Make way for the king.
迎接希优顿 迎接骠骑王
Make way for Theoden.Make way for the king.
好少人 回来的人好少
So few. So few of you have returned.
我们的人民安全了
Our people are safe.
但是却牺牲很多条人命
We have paid for it with many lives.
我的王女
My lady.
亚拉冈大人
Lord Aragorn...
他人呢?
...where is he?
他不在了
He fell.
在城墙后方派重兵驻守
Draw all our forces behind the wall.
挡住城门  哨兵守住城池
Bar the gate. And set a watch on the surround.
我的主人 不能打仗的人怎么办? 女人和小孩
What of those who cannot fight, my lord? The women and children?
带他们进入洞穴
Get them into the caves.
萨鲁曼别妄想攻下这座铜墙铁壁
Saruman's arm will have grown long indeed if he thinks he can reach us here.
圣盔谷只有一个弱点
Helm 's Deep has one weakness.
它的外墙是巨石砌成
Its outer wall is soild rock...
但是它的基座有一条渠道
...but for a small culvert at its base...
只比排水管大一点
...which is little more than a drain.
怎么做 火怎么烧得了石头?
How? How can fire undo stone?
你要用什么方法摧毁城墙?
What kind of device could bring down the wall?
只要攻下城墙 圣盔谷就会瓦解
If the wall is breached, Helm's Deep will fall.
就算能攻下城墙  还要有几千名士兵
Even if it is breached, it would take a number beyond reckoning...
才攻得进去
...thousands, to storm the Keep.
成千上万名士兵
Tens of thousands.
大人 我们没有这种大军
But, my lord, there is no such force.
一股新势力崛起
A new power is rising.
它即将获得胜利!
Its victory is at hand.
今晚
This night...
洛汗人的鲜血将染红大地
...the land will be stained with the blood of Rohan!
向圣盔谷进军
March to Helm's Deep!
不能留下活口
Leave none alive!
开战!
To war!
人类将看不到明天的曙光
There will be no dawn for Men.
看 南方有烟硝升起
Look. There's smoke to the south.
最近艾辛格一直有烟硝升起
There is always smoke rising from Isengard these days.
艾辛格?
Isengard?
很久以前
There was a time...
萨鲁曼会来我的森林漫步
...when Saruman would walk in my woods.
但是现在他却满脑子都是钢铁
But now he has a mind of metal...
还有铁轮
...and wheels.
他对大自然不再感兴趣
He no longer cares for growing things.
那是什么?
What is it?
萨鲁曼的大军
It's Saruman's army.
战争爆发了
The war has started.
愿主神保佑你
May the grace of the Valar protect you.
布理哥
Brego.
亚玟
Arwen.
是时候了
"Tollen i lû."
去维林诺的船就要开了...走吧 免得来不及
"I chair gwannar na Valannor. Si bado, no círar..."
我做了决定
I have made my choice.
他不会回来了
He is not coming back.
没有希望为何还要留恋?
Why do you linger here when there is no hope?
还是有希望
There is still hope.
就算亚拉冈在战争中活下来你们还是会分开
If Aragorn survives this war, you will still be parted.
就算亚拉冈打败索伦成为国王
If Sauron is defeated and Aragorn made king...
而你的愿望也都实现
...and all that you hope for comes true...
他还是逃不了死亡的命运
...you will still have to taste the bitterness of mortality.
不管是战死或是老死
Whether by the sword or the slow decay of time...
亚拉冈都难逃一死
...Aragorn will die.
你将得不到安慰
And there will be no comfort for you...
永远为他的死伤心难过
...no comfort to ease the pain of his passing.
他死了以后
He will come to death...
身为国王的英勇形象
...an image of the splendor of the kings of Men...
将留在世人心中永不磨灭
...in glory undimmed before the breaking of the world.
但是你 我的爱女
But you, my daughter...
将活在恒久不变的黑暗中
...you will linger on in darkness and in doubt...
就像没有星光的冬夜
...as nightfall in winter that comes without a star.
你将满怀伤悲
Here you will dwell...
住在一天一天干枯的老树下
...bound to your grief under the fading trees...
直到世界改变
...until all the world is changed...
虚度你漫长的一生
...and the long years of your life are utterly spent.
亚玟
Arwen.
你在这儿什么也没有
There is nothing for you here...
只有死亡
...only death.
你还是会爱着我的吧
"Ah im, ú'erin veleth lîn?"
当然会的 父亲
"Gerich veleth nîn, ada."
敌人的力量越来越强大
The power of the enemy is growing.
索伦将利用他的傀儡萨鲁曼
Sauron will use his puppet, Saruman...
消灭洛汗人
...to destroy the people of Rohan.
艾辛格出动邪恶大军
Isengard has been unleashed.
邪眼把目标转向刚铎
The Eye of Sauron now turns to Gondor...
人类最后的自由国土
...the last free kingdom of Men.
他将迅雷不及掩耳地进攻刚铎
His war on this country will come swiftly.
他感到魔戒离他很近
He senses the Ring is close.
魔戒持有者的意志越来越薄弱
The strength of the Ring-bearer is failing.
佛罗多的内心深处知道
In his heart, Frodo begins to understand...
这场旅程将夺去他的生命
...the quest will claim his life.
你很清楚
You know this.
你也预见到了
You have foreseen It.
这是我们必须冒的险
It Is the risk we all took.
当邪恶力量聚集  魔戒的意志力就会加强
In the gathering dark, the will of the Ring grows strong.
它一心一意想回到人类手上
It works hard now to find its way back Into the hands of Men.
因为人类很容易受到它的诱惑
Men, who are so easily seduced by Its power.
年轻的刚铎将军只要伸出手
The young captain of Gondor has but to extend his hand...
希望将魔戒占为己有  整个世界就会沦陷
...take the Ring for his own, and the world will fall.
就快了
It is close now.
就快达成他的目标
So close to achieving its goal.
索伦即将奴役世上所有生物
For Sauron will have dominion over all life on this Earth...
甚至带来中土世界的灭亡
...even unto to the ending of the world.
精灵的时代
The time of the Elves...
已经结束了
...is over.
我们该让中土世界自生自灭?
Do we leave Middle-earth to Its fate?
或是让他们孤军奋战?
Do we let them stand alone?
有什么消息?
What news?
据报萨鲁曼向洛汗国进攻
Our scouts report Saruman has attacked Rohan.
希优顿率领人民逃到圣盔谷
Theoden's people have fled to Helm's Deep.
我们必须守住边境 法拉墨  半兽人蠢蠢欲动
But we must look to our own borders. Faramir, Orcs are on the move.
索伦在召集大军
Sauron is marshaling an army.
野人部落和南蛮族聚集在黑门
Easterlings and Southrons are at the Black Gate.
- 有多少?     - 几千人 每天都在增加
- How many?     - Some thousands. More come every day.
- 谁驻守在北边河流?     - 奥斯吉力斯的五百名精兵
- Who's covering the river to the north?   - We pulled 500 men at Osgiliath.
受到攻击绝对抵挡不了
If their city is attacked, we won't hold it.
萨鲁曼从艾辛格发动攻击
Saruman attacks from Isengard.
从魔多出发
Sauron from Mordor.
会从正面攻击人类
The fight will come to Men on both fronts.
刚铎现在正虚弱
Gondor is weak.
萨鲁曼很快便会攻打我们
Sauron will strike us soon.
将会是一场硬仗
And he will strike hard.
他知道现在的我们无力抵抗
He knows now we do not have the strength to repel him.
我的手下说你们俩是间谍
My men tell me that you are Orc spies.
间谍? 先等一等
Spies? Now wait just a minute.
你们不是间谍是什么?
Well, if you're not spies, then who are you?
快说
Speak.
我们是夏尔来的哈比人
We are Hobbits of the Shire.
我的名字是佛罗多巴金斯  这是山姆卫斯詹吉
Frodo Baggins is my name, and this is Samwise Gamgee.
你的保镖吗?
Your bodyguard?
他的园丁
His gardener.
你们鬼鬼祟祟的朋友呢?
And where is your skulking friend?
滑不溜丢的小子
That gangrel creature.
那个丑八怪
He had an ill-favored look.
没有别人
There was no other.
我们七个人从瑞文戴尔出发
We set out from Rivendell with seven companions.
我们在摩瑞亚失去一个
One we lost in Moria...
有两个也是哈比人
...two were my kin...
还有一个矮人  一个精灵和两个人类
...a Dwarf there was also. And an Elf and two Men.
亚拉松之子亚拉冈和钢铎人波罗莫
Aragorn, son of Arathorn, and Boromir of Gondor.
你是波罗莫的朋友?
You're a friend of Boromir?
对
Yes.
至少我是这么想
For my part.
那听到他的死讯你一定会很难过
It will grieve you then to learn that he is dead.
死了?
Dead?
怎么会? 几时?
How? When?
你是他同伴  你倒是告诉我
As one of his companions, I'd hoped you would tell me.
如果波罗莫出事了  请告诉我
If something has happened to Boromir, we would have you tell us.
他的号角在河里洗了6天了
His horn washed up upon the riverbank, about six days past.
已经分成了两块
It was cloven in two.
我从内心知道  还不止这些
But more than this, I know it in my heart.
他是我的兄长
He was my brother.
波罗莫
Boromir!
这城市曾经是我们王国的明珠
This city was once the jewel of our kingdom.
充满光明 美景和音乐
A place of light and beauty and music.
这些应该重现!
And so it shall be once more!
要让魔多的军队知道
Let the armies of Mordor know this
我们的人民不会再次落入敌人手中
Never again will the land of my people fall into enemy hands.
奥斯吉力亚斯城已经被刚铎收复!
This city of Osgiliath has been reclaimed for Gondor!
- 为了刚铎!     - 为了刚铎!
- For Gondor!     - For Gondor!
不错的演讲  精彩 精练
Good speech. Nice and short.
这样就有更多时间喝酒!
Leaves more time for drinking!
让我们开怀畅饮!
Break out the ale! These men are thirsty!
记住今天  兄弟们
Remember today, little brother.
今天  生命是美好的
Today, life is good.
什么?
What?
他在这里
He's here.
他就不能给我们短暂的和平吗?
One moment of peace, can he not give us that?
他在哪儿?
Where is he?
刚铎的人在哪儿? 第一个呢?
Where is Gondor's finest? Where's my first-born?
父亲!
Father!
他们说你独自征服了他们的军队
They say you vanquished the enemy almost single-handedly.
夸张了  胜利同样属于法拉墨
They exaggerate. The victory belongs to Faramir also.
但是对于法拉墨  这座城依然屹立
But for Faramir, this city would still be standing.
你不驻兵保护这里?
Were you not entrusted to protect it?
我会的  但是我们人太少了
I would have done, but our numbers were too few.
哦  太少了
Oh, too few.
那你想让敌人随心所欲的进来
You let the enemy walk in and take it on a whim.
你给我的印象总是很差
Always you cast a poor reflection on me.
我不是故意的
That is not my intent.
你不信任他  而他总是在试着迎合你
You give him no credit, and yet he tries to do your will.
- 他热爱你  父亲     - 别难为法拉墨
- He loves you, Father.   - Do not trouble me with Faramir...
我知道他会帮上忙的
...I know his uses, and they are few.
我们有更多紧急的事情要谈
We have more urgent things to speak of.
瑞文戴尔的爱隆招集了一个会议
Elrond of Rivendell has called a meeting.
他没说原因  但我猜到了
He will not say why, but I have guessed its purpose.
有传言敌人的武器被找到了
It is rumored that the weapon of the enemy has been found.
一枚戒指
The One Ring.
- 埃西铎的毒药     - 掌握在精灵手中
- Isildur's Bane.   - It has fallen into the hands of the Elves.
所有人都主张: 人类 小矮人 巫师
Everyone will try to claim it: Men, Dwarves, wizards.
我们不能让这事发生  必须去刚铎
We cannot let that happen. This thing must come to Gondor.
- 刚铎     - 我知道这很危险
- Gondor.     - It's dangerous, I know.
魔戒会搜寻弱小者的恐惧
Ever the Ring will seek to corrupt the hearts of lesser Men.
但是你很坚强
But you, you are strong. And our need is great.
我们在流血  我们的人在死去
It is our blood which is being spilled, our people who are dying.
萨鲁曼正抓紧集结军队
Sauron is biding his time. He's massing fresh armies.
他会回来的
He will return.
如果他来了  我们没有力量阻止他
And when he does, we will be powerless to stop him.
我们必须走
You must go.
带回给我强大的礼物
Bring me back this mighty gift.
不  我应该和我的人民在一起  而不是去瑞文戴尔
No. My place is here with my people. Not in Rivendell.
- 你会反悔吗?     - 如果有必要去瑞文戴尔
- Would you deny your own father?  - If there is need to go to Rivendell...
- 我来代替他     - 你?
- ...send me in his stead.     - You?
我明白了
Oh, I see.
一个刚铎之子法拉墨展示品格的机会
A chance for Faramir, captain of Gondor, to show his quality.
我认为不是
I think not.
我相信这任务  非你兄长莫属
I trust this mission only to your brother.
他不会让我失望的
The one who will not fail me.
记住今天  小兄弟
Remember today, little brother.
法拉墨将军
Captain Faramir!
我们找到另一个家伙
We found the third one.
你跟我走 来吧
You must come with me. Now.
下面
Down there.
谁闯进禁忌之池格杀勿论
To enter the Forbidden Pool bears the penalty of death.
他们在等我的命令
They wait for my command.
我该下令吗?
Shall I shoot?
池塘的水好清凉
The rock and pool is nice and cool
多么香甜多汁啊
So juicy sweet
我唯一的愿望就是抓到鱼儿
Our only wish to catch a fish
多么香甜多汁啊
So juicy sweet
慢着
Wait.
这生物对我有义务
This creature is bound to me.
我对他也有责任
And I to him.
他是我们的向导
He is our guide.
请
Please...
让我下去找他
...let me go down to him.
史麦戈
Smeagol.
主人在这儿
Master is here.
来 史麦戈
Come, Smeagol.
相信主人
Trust master. Come.
我们一定要马上走吗?
We must go now?
史麦戈 你要相信主人
Smeagol, you must trust master.
跟我来 快点!
Follow me. Come on.
来
Come.
来 史麦戈
Come, Smeagol.
史麦戈乖 很好
Nice Smeagol. That's it.
来啊
Come on.
别伤害他
Don't hurt him!
史麦戈 别挣扎 听我说
Smeagol, don't struggle. Smeagol, listen to me.
主人
Master!
你为什么要哭 史麦戈?
Why does it cry, Smeagol?
坏人伤害我们
Cruel Men hurts us.
主人骗了我们
Master tricksed us.
他当然骗了我们
Of course he did.
我就跟你说他很奸诈
I told you he was tricksy.
我跟你说他很虚伪
I told you he was false.
主人是朋友
Master is our friend.
我们的朋友
Our friend.
主人出卖了我们
Master betrayed us.
不! 这不关你的事
No. Not its business.
别管我们
Leave us alone!
臭哈比人
Filthy little Hobbitses!
他们偷我们的东西
They stole it from us!
不  不
No. No.
他们偷走什么?
What did they steal?
我的宝贝
My precious!
我们一定要逃走
We have to get out of here.
你快走吧! 马上走!
You go. Go, now.
你可以办得到的
You can do it.
快用魔戒 佛罗多先生
Use the Ring, Mr. Frodo.
就这么一次
Just this once.
戴上它
Put it on.
消失掉
Disappear.
我不行
I can't.
你说的对 山姆
You were right, Sam.
你试着告诉我  但是
You tried to tell me but...
对不起
I'm sorry.
魔戒控制了我
The Ring's taking me, Sam.
我一戴上魔戒
If I put it on...
他就会找到我
...he'll find me.
他就会看到我
He'll see.
佛罗多先生
Mr. Frodo...
原来这就是所有谜团的答案
So this is the answer to all the riddles.
我在荒郊野外找到你们
Here in the Wild I have you...
两个哈比人
...two Halflings...
我有一群忠心部下
...and a host of men at my call.
至尊魔戒也在我的掌心
The Ring of Power within my grasp.
我这刚铎大将 法拉墨
A chance for Faramir, captain of Gondor...
将证明自己的能力
...to show his quality.
不!
No!
住手!
Stop it!
让他走!
Leave him alone.
你不明白吗?
Don't you understand?
他一定要摧毁它!
He's got to destroy it!
所以我们才要去魔多
That's where we're going, into Mordor.
把它丢进末日火山烈焰
To the Mountain of Fire!
奥斯吉力亚斯受到攻击  他们请你调派援兵
Osgiliath is under attack. They call for reinforcements.
求求你  他身负重担
Please. It's such a burden.
你不肯帮他吗?
Will you not help him?
将军
Captain?
准备出发
Prepare to leave.
魔戒将被带到刚铎
The Ring will go to Gondor.
- 他还活着     - 他人呢? 他人呢?
- He's alive!     - Where is he? Where is he?
让开  我要宰了他
Get out of the way! I'm going to kill him!
你是我见过最幸运 最机智
You are the luckiest, the canniest...
最不怕死的家伙
...and the most reckless man I ever knew.
谢天谢地
Bless you, laddie.
金雳 国王呢?
Gimli, where is the king?
你看起来好惨
You look terrible.
一支大军?
A great host, you say?
- 艾辛格大军倾巢而出     - 多少人?
- All Isengard is emptied.     - How many?
至少有一万人
Ten thousand strong at least.
一万人?
Ten thousand?
这支大军只有一个目的
It is an army bred for a single purpose:
摧毁人类世界
To destroy the world of Men.
他们入夜就会攻到
They will be here by nightfall.
让他们来吧!
Let them come!
让每个士兵和壮丁
I want every man and strong lad able to bear arms...
佩带武器 今晚准备迎敌
...to be ready for battle by nightfall.
我们在上面守住通道和城门
We will cover the causeway and the gate from above.
没有人攻得下深溪墙
No army has ever breached the Deeping Wall...
或是攻进号角堡
...or set foot inside the Hornburg!
他们可不是低能的半兽人
This is no rabble of mindless Orcs.
他们是强兽人
These are Uruk-hai.
骁勇善战  武器精良
Their armour is thick and their shields broad.
我身经百战 矮人先生
I have fought many wars, Master Dwarf.
我知道怎么防卫我的堡垒
I know how to defend my own keep.
这座碉堡可以说是滴水不漏
They will break upon this fortress like water on rock.
萨鲁曼大军会烧杀掳掠  我们以前见识过的
Saruman's hordes will pillage and burn. We've seen it before.
农作物可以再耕种
Crops can be resown...
家园可以再重建
...homes rebuilt.
我们在这座铜墙铁壁内
Within these walls...
撑得绝对比他们久
...we will outlast them.
他们来是要把洛汗人赶尽杀绝的
They do not come to destroy Rohan's crops or villages.
把洛汗人赶尽杀绝
They come to destroy its people down to the last child.
你要我怎么办?
What would you have me do?
看看他们
Look at my men.
他们就快失去勇气
Their courage hangs by a thread.
即便这是我们的末日  我也要让他们奋战到底
If this is to be our end, then I would have them make such an end...
好让世人永远记得
...as to be worthy of remembrance.
派出骑士 国王
Send out riders, my lord.
你一定要搬救兵
You must call for aid.
谁会来救我们?
And who will come?
精灵?
Elves?
矮人?
Dwarves?
我们不像你有那么多朋友
We are not so lucky in our friends as you.
古老的同盟早已瓦解
The old alliances are dead.
- 刚铎会派出救兵 王上     - 刚铎?
- Gondor will answer.     - Gondor?!
西谷沦陷时他们在哪里?
Where was Gondor when the Westfold fell?!
敌人围攻时他们在哪里?
Where was Gondor when our enemies closed in around us?!
刚铎在哪...
Where was Gon...?
不 亚拉冈
No, my Lord Aragorn...
我们只能孤军奋战
...we are alone.
把妇女和孩子带进山洞里去
Get the women and children into the caves.
我们需要时间准备
We need more time to lay provisions...
没时间了  开战了
There is no time. War is upon us.
封锁大门
Secure the gate.
我们树人不插手
We Ents have not troubled...
人类和巫师的战争
...about the wars of Men and wizards...
已经有好久了
...for a very long time.
但是现在要发生的事
But now, something is about to happen...
没发生过
...that has not happened...
有好长一段时间了
...for an age.
树人会议
Entmoot.
那是什么?
What's that?
那是一个集会
'Tis a gathering.
什么样的集会?
A gathering of what?
山毛榉 橡树
Beech. Oak.
栗树 白杨树
Chestnut. Ash.
很好  很好  很好
Good. Good. Good.
很多树人都来了
Many have come.
我们要决定树人
Now we must decide if the Ents...
该不该参战
...will go to war.
撤退 快进洞穴!
Move back! Move to the caves!
继续走 快点!
Come on, people! Quickly, now!
沿着城墙储备
We'll place the reserves along the wall.
可以从门上面支援弓箭手
They can support the archers from above the gate.
亚拉冈  你需要休息
Aragorn, you must rest.
半死对我们没用
You're no use to us half alive.
亚拉冈
Aragorn!
我会和女人们一起到洞里去
I'm to be sent with the women into the caves.
这是一个光荣的机会
That is an honorable charge.
照顾孩子们  寻找食物  等待勇士们归来
To mind the children, to find food and bedding when the men return.
那里的名声怎么样?
What renown is there in that?
女王  这是英勇而不是为了名声
My lady, a time may come for valor without renown.
谁负责最后防线?
Who then will your people look to in the last defense?
- 让我站到你那边     - 不是我的力量可以决定的
- Let me stand at your side.  - It is not in my power to command it.
你不能命令其他人留下!
You do not command the others to stay!
他们和你一起战斗因为他们不想和你分开
They fight beside you because they would not be parted from you.
因为他们热爱你
Because they love you.
对不起
I'm sorry.
农夫 老人 小孩
Farmers, farriers, stable boys.
这些人根本无法作战
These are no soldiers.
- 他们多半见不到冬天了     - 人太少了
- Most have seen too many winters.     - Or too few.
看看他们  他们的恐惧
Look at them. They're frightened.
从他们眼中你可以看出来
I can see it in their eyes.
那我也该跟着他们一起牺牲
Then I shall die as one of them!
让他去吧  伙计
Let him go, lad.
让他去
Let him be.
会使剑的人都去领武器了
Every villager able to wield a sword has been sent to the armoury.
王上?
My lord?
加姆林 我是谁?
Who am I, Gamling?
您是我们的国王
You are our king, sire.
你相信你的国王吗?
And do you trust your king?
王上 您的士兵都将追随您
Your men, my lord will follow you to whatever end.
无论死活
To whatever end.
骠悍的战马和骑士在哪里?
Where is the horse and the rider?
胜利的号角在哪里?
Where is the horn that was blowing?
它们早就消失了  就像落在高山的雨滴
They have passed like rain on the mountains.
或是拂过草原的微风
Like wind in the meadow.
昔日的荣耀就像太阳西下
The days have gone down in the West...
黯然消失在山后
...behind the hills...
被黑暗笼罩
...into Shadow.
怎么会变成这样?
How did it come to this?
已经很长时间了
It's been going for hours.
他们肯定已经做出决定了
They must have decided something by now.
决定? 没有
Decided? No.
我们刚道完
We only just finished saying...
早安
...good morning.
但现在是半夜啊
But it's nighttime already.
你们不能没完没了啊
You can't take forever.
别着急
Don't be hasty.
我们没时间了!
We're running out of time!
快 快到外墙
Move! Move to the outer wall.
把剑给我
Give me your sword.
你叫什么?
What is your name?
哈拉斯  哈玛之子
Haleth, son of Hama, my lord.
大家都说我们活不过今晚
The men are saying we will not live out the night.
他们说没有希望了
They say that it is hopeless.
这是把好剑
This is a good sword.
哈玛之子哈拉斯
Haleth, son of Hama...
永远都有希望
...there is always hope.
我们相信你 你也没令人失望
We have trusted you this far. You have not led us astray.
原谅我
Forgive me.
我不该绝望
I was wrong to despair.
还来的及改改这身锁子甲
We had time, I'd get this adjusted.
胸口这儿有点紧
It's a little tight across the chest.
那不是半兽人号角
That is no Orc horn.
快去叫国王
Send for the king.
- 打开大门!     - 打开大门!
- Open the gate!     - Open up the gate!
这怎么可能?
How is this possible?
我带来爱隆王的信息
I bring word from Elrond of Rivendell.
精灵曾和人类结为同盟
An alliance once existed between Elves and Men.
在很久以前并肩作战
Long ago we fought and died together.
我们是来实践我们的盟约的
We come to honor that allegiance.
太欢迎了
You are most welcome.
我们很荣幸再跟人类并肩作战
We are proud to fight alongside Men once more.
你挑的什么烂位置
You could have picked a better spot.
希望你的好运气能撑过今晚
Well, lad, whatever luck you live by, let's hope it lasts the night.
你的朋友都来了 亚拉冈
Your friends are with you, Aragorn.
希望他们熬得过今晚
Let's hope they last the night.
- 发生什么事?     - 你要我说给你听?
- What's happening out there?   - Shall I describe it to you?
还是替你找垫脚箱?
Or would you like me to find you a box?
开战了
So it begins.
有没有射中?
Did they hit anything?
齐射
Give them a volley.
- 放箭!     - 放箭!
- Fire!     - Fire!
把他们送来领死  来啊!
Send them to me! Come on!
很好!
Good!
剑! 剑!
Swords! Swords!
勒苟拉斯! 我痛宰了两个!
Legolas! Two already!
我杀了17个了!
I'm on 17!
我可不能输给尖耳朵的家伙!
I'll have no pointy-ear outscoring me!
19!
Nineteen!
梅里
Merry.
我们同意了
We have just agreed.
同意什么?
Yes?
我在树人会议上提到你们
I have told your names to the Entmoot...
我们都同意
...and we have agreed...
你们不是半兽人
...you are not Orcs.
那真是好消息
Well, that's good news.
那萨鲁曼呢? 你们有什么关于他的决定?
And what about Saruman? Have you come to a decision about him?
别急 梅里雅达克
Now, don't be hasty, Master Meriadoc.
别急?
Hasty?
我们的朋友在打仗
Our friends are out there.
他们需要我们的帮忙  他们不能孤军奋战
They need our help. They cannot fight this war on their own.
战争? 没错
War? Yes.
战争影响了大家
It affects us all.
树身 树根和树枝
Tree, root and twig.
不过你要了解 小哈比人
But you must understand, young Hobbit...
用古树人语说话要花很久时间
...it takes a long time to say anything in Old Entish...
如非必要我们是不会开口的
...and we never say anything unless it is worth taking.
17!18!
Seventeen! Eighteen!
19!
Nineteen!
20!
Twenty!
21!
Twenty-one!
堤道!
Causeway!
就这些吗?
Is this it?
你就只有这点能耐吗 萨鲁曼?
Is this is all you can conjure, Saruman?
抵住门!
Brace the gate!
挡住他们 死守住!
Hold them! Stand firm!
亚拉冈!
Aragorn!
金雳!
Gimli!
树人无法力挽狂澜
The Ents cannot hold back this storm.
我们只能像以前一样逆来顺受
We must weather such things as we have always done.
你们怎么能这么决定?
How can that be your decision?!
这不是我们的战争
This is not our war.
可是你们也属于这世界!
But you're part of this world!
不是吗?!
Aren't you?!
你们一定要帮忙 拜托
You must help. Please.
你们一定要想想办法
You must do something.
你很年轻也很勇敢  梅里
You are young and brave, Master Merry.
但是你的旅程已经结束了
But your part in this tale is over.
回家吧
Go back to your home.
也许树须说的对
Maybe Treebeard right.
我们也无能为力 梅里
We don't belong here, Merry.
我们太渺小了
It's too big for us.
我们能做什么呢?
What can we do in the end?
我们还有夏尔
We've got the Shire.
也许我们应该回家
Maybe we should go home.
艾辛格的战火会蔓延
The fires of Isengard will spread...
塔克镇和雄鹿地树林也会燃烧精光
...and the woods of Tuckborough and Buckland will burn.
还有
And...
世上一切绿色的  美好的东西都会毁灭
And all that was once green and good in this world will be gone.
夏尔也会毁于一旦
There won't be a Shire, Pippin.
亚拉冈!
Aragorn!
撤退到圣盔谷!
Fall back to the Keep!
叫他们撤退
Get your men out of there!
哈尔达!
Haldir!
怎么了  你们干嘛停下来?
What are you doing? What are you stopping for?
哈尔达!
Haldir!
抵住大门!
Brace the gate!
挡住他们!
Hold them!
去大门  把剑拔出来!
To the gate. Draw your swords!
让开!
Make way!
我们抵挡不了多久!
We cannot hold much longer!
- 挡住他们!     - 你要多久?
- Hold them!     - How long do you need?
你们能撑多久就多久
As long as you can give me.
金雳!
Gimli!
用木头!
Timbers!
挡住大门!
Brace the gate!
来吧 我们能干掉他们
Come on. We can take them.
太远了
It's a long way.
把我丢过去
Toss me.
- 什么?     - 我跳不了那么远!
- What?      - I cannot jump the distance!
把我丢过去!
You'll have to toss me!
别跟精灵小子说
Don't tell the Elf.
我会守口如瓶
Not a word.
撑住大门!
Shore up the door!
- 让开!     - 跟我到路障处
- Make way!     - Follow me to the barricade.
注意背后!
Watch our backs!
- 这儿再来一根!     - 高一点!
- Throw another one over here!     - Higher!
门抵牢!
Hold fast the gate!
金雳! 亚拉冈! 快回来!
Gimli! Aragorn! Get out of there!
亚拉冈!
Aragorn!
叫大家撤退
Pull everybody back.
叫他们回来
Pull them back.
撤退!
Fall back!
他们攻进来了!
They have broken through!
城堡给攻破了  撤退!
The castle is breached. Retreat!
- 撤退!     - 撤退!
- Fall back!     - Retreat!
快把他们带进去!
Hurry! Inside. Get them inside!
进去碉堡!
Into the Keep!
我把你们带到森林西边
I will leave you at the western borders of the forest.
你们往北走就可以回到家
You can make your way north to your homeland from there.
等等 停下来!
Wait! Stop!
停下来!
Stop!
转回去
Turn around.
- 转回去 带我们到南边去     - 南边?
- Turn around. Take us south.     - South?
那不就是去艾辛格的路
But that will lead you past Isengard.
一点也没错
Yes. Exactly.
走南边  我们可以悄悄越过萨鲁曼
If we go south, we can slip past Saruman unnoticed.
越危险的地方  越是安全
The closer we are to danger, the farther we are from harm.
他一定料想不到
It's the last thing he'll expect.
我不太明白
That doesn't make sense to me.
不过你们个子很小
But then you are very small.
也许你们是对的
Perhaps you're right.
就南边吧
South it is, then.
抓紧了 小哈比人
Hold on, little Shirelings.
我一向都喜欢往南走
I always like going south.
就好像下坡一样
Somehow it feels like going downhill.
你疯啦? 我们会被逮到
Are you mad? We'll be caught.
才不会
No, we won't.
这次不会
Not this time.
你看!
Look!
奥斯吉力亚斯在燃烧!
Osgiliath burns!
魔多大军攻来了
Mordor has come.
魔戒也救不了刚铎
The Ring will not save Gondor.
它只有毁灭的力量
It has only the power to destroy.
求求你
Please...
让我走
...let me go.
快点!
Faramir!
法拉墨 你一定要让我走!
You must let me go!
那一群田鼠
And those little family of field mice...
它们爬到我身上好痒哦
...that climb up sometimes, and they tickle me awfully.
它们老是爬到
They're always trying to get somewhere where they...
这儿有很多树是我的朋友
Many of these trees were my friends.
他们还是种子时我就认识他们
Creatures I had known from nut and acorn.
很遗憾 树须
I'm sorry, Treebeard.
他们有自己的声音
They had voices of their own.
萨鲁曼
Saruman.
一个巫师不该这么做!
A wizard should know better!
没有更强烈的字眼
There is no curse in Elvish...
在精灵语  树人语或是人类语中
...Entish or the tongues of Men...
来诅咒这种恶行
...for this treachery.
看啊  这些树在动!
Look! The trees! They're moving!
他们要去哪儿?
Where are they going?
他们和兽人有些帐要算
They have business with the Orcs.
我今晚要用巨石和岩石摧毁艾辛格
My business is with Isengard tonight with rock and stone.
好啊
Yes.
来吧 朋友们
Come, my friends.
树人要开战了
The Ents are going to war.
我们很可能
It is likely...
会走向灭亡之路
...that we go to our doom.
这是树人最后的一战
Last march of the Ents.
半兽人占领了东岸  他们的数量太多
Faramir! Orcs have taken the eastern shore. Their numbers are too great.
到晚上我们就会溃不成军
By nightfall we will be overrun.
佛罗多先生?
Mr. Frodo?
它在召唤他  邪眼就快看到我
It's calling to him, Sam. His Eye is almost on me.
撑着点 佛罗多先生你不会有事的
Hold on, Mr. Frodo. You'll be all right.
把他带去见父王
Take them to my father.
就说法拉墨送上大礼
Tell him Faramir sends a mighty gift.
一个足以扭转局势的武器
A weapon that will change our fortunes in this war.
你想知道波罗莫的遭遇吗?
Do you want to know what happened to Boromir?
你想知道你兄长为什么死吗?
You want to know why your brother died?
他誓言保护佛罗多  却想夺走魔戒
He tried to take the Ring from Frodo after swearing an oath to protect him!
想杀了他!
He tried to kill him!
魔戒把你兄长逼疯!
The Ring drove your brother mad!
小心!
Watch out!
佛罗多先生?
Mr. Frodo?
他们在这儿
They're here.
他们来了
They've come.
戒灵!
Nazg鹟!
待在这儿 躲起来
Stay here. Keep out of sight.
快找掩护!
Take cover!
堡垒被攻陷
The fortress is taken.
我们输了
It is over.
你说这座堡垒绝不会沦陷  他们会奋战到底
You said this fortress would never fall while your men defend it.
他们还在浴血奋战
They still defend it. They have died defending it.
他们攻进来了!
They're breaking in!
他们破门而入了!
They're past the door!
女人小孩没办法逃出去吗?
Is there no other way for the women and children to get out of the caves?
没别的路了吗?
Is there no other way?
有一条通道 直接到山上
There is one passage. It leads into the mountains.
不过逃不了多远  到处都有强兽人
But they will not get far. The Uruk-hai are too many.
叫女人小孩进入通道上山
Send word for the women and children to make for the mountain pass.
- 堵住入口!     - 死了这么多人
- And barricade the entrance!     - So much death.
人类该怎么对抗这种仇恨?
What can Men do against such reckless hate?
跟我一起冲出去
Ride out with me.
冲出去迎敌
Ride out and meet them.
为了光荣的牺牲
For death and glory.
为了洛汗
For Rohan.
为了你的人民
For your people.
太阳出来了
The sun is rising.
五天后等待我的出现
Look to my coming at first light on the fifth day.
黎明时
At dawn...
向东方看
...look to the east.
好
Yes.
圣盔锤手的号角
The horn of Helm Hammerhand...
将会响起
...shall sound in the Deep...
最后一次
...one last time.
好耶!
Yes!
这是我们一起拔剑抗敌的时刻
Let this be the hour when we draw swords together.
邪恶兵团 领死吧
Fell deeds, awake.
我要以满腔热血
Now for wrath...
和无比勇气  迎接浴血黎明
...now for ruin and a red dawn.
骠骑勇士 冲啊
Forth Eorlingas!
甘道夫
Gandalf.
希优顿王孤军奋战
Theoden King stands alone.
他并不孤单
Not alone.
洛汗弟兄们!
Rohirrim!
拯救国王!
To the king!
好啊!
Yes!
丢得好 好准
A hit. A fine hit.
撞破水坝!
Break the dam!
让河水泄洪!
Release the river!
皮聘 抓紧了!
Pippin! Hold on!
抓紧了 小哈比人!
Hold on, little Hobbits.
你在干嘛?
What are you doing?
你要去哪儿?
Where are you going?
是我呀
It's me.
我是你的山姆
It's your Sam.
你不认得我了吗?
Don't you know your Sam?
我办不到 山姆
I can't do this, Sam.
我知道
I know.
这不公平
It's all wrong.
我们根本就不该来
By rights, we shouldn't even be here.
但是我们来了
But we are.
这就像我们听过的精彩故事 佛罗多先生
It's like in the great stories, Mr. Frodo.
描述伟大的事迹
The ones that really mattered.
有时候你不想知道结局
And sometimes you didn't want to know the end...
因为怎么可能有快乐结局?
...because how could the end be happy?
这世界怎么可能回到从前?
How could the world go back to the way It was...
发生了这么多可怕的事
...when so much bad had happened?
胜利!
Victory!
我们胜利了!
We have victory!
但是最后  阴影终究会过去
But In the end, It's only a passing thing this shadow.
就连黑暗也会消失
Even darkness must pass.
崭新的一天将会来临
A new day will come.
太阳也会散发更明亮的光芒
And when the sun shines, It will shine out the clearer.
这才是让人永生难忘有意义的感人故事
Those were the stories that stayed with you that meant something.
就算你太年轻不明白为什么
Even If you were too small to understand why.
但是我想我明白了 佛罗多先生
But I think, Mr. Frodo, I do understand.
我现在明白了
I know now.
故事的主角
Folk in those stories...
有很多机会放弃 但是他们并没有
...had lots of chances of turning back, only they didn't.
他们决定勇往直前
They kept going...
因为他们抱着一种信念
...because they were holding on to something.
我们抱着什么信念 山姆?
What are we holding on to, Sam?
这世上一定存在着善良 佛罗多先生
That there's some good in this world, Mr. Frodo.
值得我们奋战到底
And it's worth fighting for.
我想我们终于互相理解了 佛罗多巴金斯
I think at last we understand one another, Frodo Baggins.
你很清楚我国的法律  你父王的命令
You know the laws of our country, the laws of your father.
你放他们走就会被处死
If you let them go, your life will be forfeit.
那我宁愿死
Then it is forfeit.
放了他们
Release them.
别追到树林里去!
Stay out of the forest!
别追了!
Keep away from the trees!
最终数字
Final count...
- 42     - 42?
- Forty-two     - Forty-two?
对于一个尖耳朵的精灵王子来说  算不错了
That's not bad for a pointy-eared Elvish princeling.
我正坐在第43个身上
I myself am sitting pretty on 43.
- 43     - 它已经死了
- Forty-three.     - He was already dead.
- 它还在抽搐     - 它在抽搐
- He was twitching.     - He was twitching...
是因为我的斧子正砍在它神经系统上!
...because he's got my ax embedded in his nervous system!
-他好像不开心  是吗?     - 一点都不开心   梅里
- He doesn't look too happy, does he?   - Not too happy at all, Merry.
我想  上面的景色一定不错
Still, I suppose the view would be quite nice from up there.
哦  是的  看来它还挺牢固啊
Oh, yes. It's a quality establishment.
我听说材料非常好
I hear the staff are very good.
- 你在干什么?     - 没什么
- What are you doing?     - Nothing.
- 世界又恢复平常了     - 不  还没有
- The world back to normal, that's all.     - No, it isn't.
我饿了
I'm starving.
看看能不能有运气在附近找到点像样的吃的
Good luck trying to find something decent around here.
也许只有死老鼠和发霉的面包
Probably dead rats and moldy bread.
萨鲁曼的储藏室!
Saruman's storeroom!
真不敢相信
I don't believe it.
不会吧
It can't be.
- 是的!     - 长端叶
- It is!     - Longbottom Leaf.
最棒的烟叶
The finest pipe-weed in South Farthing.
太好了  每人一桶
It's perfect. One barrel each.
等等
Wait.
我们该分给树须吗?
Do you think we should share it with Treebeard?
分?
Share it?
不  不
No. No.
这是死掉的植物
Dead plant and all that.
他不会理解的
Don't think he'd understand.
也许还是远亲呢
Could be a distant relative.
我懂了
I get it.
别着急
Don't be hasty.
正是
Exactly.
Bar-hrum
Bar-hrum.
这是旧的下水道
This is the old sewer.
一直通到城市边缘
Runs right under the river through to the edge of the city.
在树林里可以躲起来
You'll find cover in the woods there.
队长
Captain Faramir...
你很了不起  先生
...you have shown your quality, sir.
非常高尚
The very highest.
夏尔一定是个了不起的地方
The Shire must truly be a great realm, Master Gamgee...
那里园丁一定很受尊重
...where gardeners are held in high honor.
到了树林  你们会走那条路?
What road will you take once you reach the woods?
咕鲁说有条路
Gollum says there's a path...
一直通到山上
...near Minas Morgul that climbs up into the mountains.
克里斯 恩格?
Cirith Ungol?
- 是吗?     - 不是
- Is that its name?     - No.
不!
No!
- 是的     - 佛尔多
- Yes.     - Frodo...
他们说米那斯魔窟笼罩着可怕的黑暗
...they say a dark terror dwells in the passes above Minas Morgul.
- 不能走那条路     - 这是唯一的路
- You cannot go that way.     - It is the only way.
主人说要到魔多
Master says we must go to Mordor, so we must try.
我必须去
I must.
去吧  我们祝福你
Go, Frodo. Go with the goodwill of all Men.
谢谢
Thank you.
如果你敢伤害他们  你就离死不远了
May death find you quickly if you bring them to harm.
快  跟上
Come on, keep up.
佛尔多先生不是要让骑士伤害你
Mr. Frodo didn't mean for them Rangers to hurt you.
你知道的  是吗?
You know that, don't you?
他想救你  知道吗?
He was trying to save you, see?
救我?
Save me?
别怀恨
So there's no hard feelings.
- 忘了吧     - 不  我没有怨言
- Forgive and forget.     - No, no, no hard feelings.
咕鲁  咕鲁
Gollum, Gollum.
是  主人
Yes, master.
- 真是好人     - 你也不错
- Nice Hobbits.     - Very decent of you.
很不错  咕鲁
Very decent, indeed, Gollum.
索伦在盛怒下一定会报复
Sauron's wrath will be terrible, his retribution swift.
圣盔谷之役结束了
The battle for Helm's Deep is over.
但是中土世界之战才刚开始
The battle for Middle-earth is about to begin.
希望都放在两个小哈比人身上
All our hopes now lie with two little Hobbits...
他们在荒野游荡
...somewhere in the wilderness.
也许我们会被编入故事或诗歌
I wonder if we'll ever be put into songs or tales.
什么?
What?
也许以后会有人说咱们听听佛罗多和魔戒的故事
I wonder if people will ever say, "Let's hear about Frodo and the Ring."
另一个人就说 是啊 那是我最爱听的故事
And they'll say, "Yes! That's one of my favorite stories."
佛罗多好勇敢 对吧 爸爸?
"Frodo was really courageous, wasn't he, Dad?"
是啊 孩子
"Yes, my boy.
他是最有名的哈比人  了不起
The most famousest of Hobbits. And that's saying a lot."
忘了一个重要人物
Well, you've left out one of the chief characters:
山姆卫斯勇士
"Samwise the Brave."
我想多听听山姆的事
I want to hear more about Sam.
佛罗多没有山姆就走不远
Frodo wouldn't have got far without Sam.
不 佛罗多先生  别开玩笑了  认真点
Now, Mr. Frodo, you shouldn't make fun. I was being serious.
我是认真的
So was I.
山姆卫斯勇士
"Samwise the Brave."
史麦戈?
Smeagol?
我们不会等你的
We're not going to wait for you. Come on.
主人
Master.
主人照顾我们
Master looks after us.
主人不会伤害我们的
Master wouldn't hurt us.
主人不守信用
Master broke his promise.
别问史麦戈
Don't ask Smeagol.
可怜的史麦戈
Poor, poor Smeagol.
主人出卖了我们!
Master betrayed us.
邪恶  狡猾  虚伪
Wicked. Tricksy. False.
我们该扭断他的脖子
We ought to wring his filthy little neck.
杀了他! 杀了他!
Kill him! Kill him!
杀了他们两个!
Kill them both!
然后抢走宝贝
And then we take the precious...
自己当主人!
...and we be the master!
可是那胖哈比人  他知道
But the fat Hobbit, he knows.
他老是盯着我们
Eyes always watching.
那就把他的眼睛刺瞎
Then we stabs them out.
把他眼珠挖掉  让他爬着走
Put out his eyeses and make him crawl.
好 好
Yes. Yes. Yes.
杀了他们两个
Kill them both.
好 不好!
Yes. No! No!
太冒险了 太冒险了
It's too risky. It's too risky.
他跑哪儿去了?
Where is he? Where has he gone?
- 好了 咕鲁 你在哪儿?     - 史麦戈?
- Hey, Gollum! Where are you?     - Smeagol?
我们可以让她下手
We could let her do it.
是啊 她可以下毒手
Yes. She could do it.
没错 宝贝 她可以下手
Yes, precious, she could.
等他们死了就可以把它拿走
And then we takes it once they're dead.
要等他们死了
Once they're dead.
来吧 小哈比人  还有好长的路要走
Come on, Hobbits. Long ways to go yet.
史麦戈会带你们去
Smeagol will show you the way.
跟我来
Follow me.